<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S1139-76322012000400002</identifier>
<datestamp>2013-01-14</datestamp>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Castillo Martín,F. del]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Baquero Artigao,F.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Calle Cabrera,T. de la]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[López Robles,M. V.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ruiz-Canela Cáceres,J.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alfayate Miguélez,S.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Moraga Llop,F.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cilleruelo Ortega,M. J.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Calvo Rey,C.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Otitis media aguda]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Amoxicilina]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Etiología]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Sintomatología]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Asociación Española de Pediatría de Atención Primaria]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Pediatría Atención Primaria  v.14 n.55 2012]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2012-09-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1139-76322012000400002</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Documento de consenso sobre etiología, diagnóstico y tratamiento de la otitis media aguda]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Consensus document on the aetiology, diagnosis and treatment of acute otitis media]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Se presenta el documento de consenso sobre otitis media aguda (OMA) de la Sociedad Española de Infectología Pediátrica (SEIP), la Sociedad Española de Pediatría Extrahospitalaria y Atención Primaria (SEPEAP), la Sociedad Española de Urgencias Pediátricas (SEUP) y la Asociación Española de Pediatría de Atención Primaria (AEPap). Se analizan la etiología de la enfermedad y los posibles cambios de esta después de la introducción de la vacunas antineumocócicas 7-valente, 10-valente y 13-valente. Se hace una propuesta diagnóstica basada en la clasificación de la OMA en confirmada o probable. Se considera OMA confirmada si hay coincidencia de tres criterios: comienzo agudo, signos de ocupación del oído medio (u otorrea) y signos o síntomas inflamatorios, como otalgia o intensa hiperemia timpánica, y OMA probable cuando existan solo dos criterios. Se propone como tratamiento antibiótico de elección la amoxicilina oral en dosis de 80 mg/kg/día repartidas cada ocho horas. El tratamiento con amoxicilina-ácido clavulánico en dosis de 80 mg/kg/día se indica si el niño es menor de seis meses, en lactantes con clínica grave (fiebre >39 ºC o dolor muy intenso), cuando haya historia familiar de secuelas óticas por OMA o un fracaso terapéutico de la amoxicilina.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[We present the consensus document on acute otitis media (AOM) written by the Spanish Society of Pediatric Infectology (SEIP), the Spanish Society of Outpatient and Primary Care Pediatrics (SEPEAP), the Spanish Society of Pediatric Emergency Care (SEUP) and the Spanish Association of Primary Care Pediatrics (AEPAP). The document analyses the etiology of the disease and the possible shifts in it following the introduction of the 7-valent, 10-valent, and 13-valent pneumococcal vaccines. The document proposes diagnosing AOM as confirmed or probable. The AOM diagnosis is considered confirmed if three criteria are met: acute onset, signs of fluid in the middle ear (or otorrhea), and symptoms of inflammation, such as otalgia or marked erythema in the middle ear, and considered probable when only two of these criteria are met. The proposed first choice for antibiotic treatment is 80 mg/kg/day of amoxicillin administered orally in doses at eight hour intervals. Treatment with amoxicillin-clavulanic acid in doses of 80 mg/kg/day are indicated in children younger than six months, in infants with a severe presentation (fever >39 ºC or acute pain), when there is a family history of AOM sequelae, or in cases of amoxicillin treatment failure.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
