<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S1699-695X2008000100003</identifier>
<datestamp>2009-05-04</datestamp>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Orueta Sánchez,Ramón]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rodríguez de Cossío,Ángela]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Carmona de la Morena,Javier]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Moreno Álvarez-Vijande,Almudena]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[García López,Antonio]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pintor Córdoba,Cristina]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Anciano frágil]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Calidad de vida]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Castellano-Manchega de Medicina de Familia y Comunitaria]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Revista Clínica de Medicina de Familia  v.2 n.3 2008]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2008-02-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1699-695X2008000100003</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Anciano Frágil y Calidad de Vida]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Fragile Elderly people and Quality of life]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Objetivo. Conocer el grado subjetivo de deterioro de la calidad de vida en ancianos con criterios de fragilidad. Diseño. Estudio observacional, descriptivo, transversal. Emplazamiento. Atención Primaria, Zona de Salud. Participantes. Ancianos con criterios de fragilidad. Criterio de exclusión: ancianos frágiles con deterioro físico/psíquico que impidiera cumplimentar los cuestionarios o negativa a participar (total 8,5%). Mediciones principales. Cuestionario de calidad de vida Nottingham Health Profile (NHP) para la variable principal. Otras variables recogidas: sociodemográficas (edad, sexo y convivencia), número de enfermedades crónicas y de fármacos consumidos y el cuestionario de capacidad funcional de Barthel. Resultados. Edad media de 81,4 años, 67,5% mujeres, 33,7% vivían solos, número medio de 3,2 patologías crónicas y de 4,7 fármacos consumidos. El porcentaje de deterioro global en el NHP fue de 25,6 (IC95% 22,8-28,3), siendo dicho deterioro variable en cada una de las dimensiones: energía (26,1; 21,2-31,0), dolor (20,5; 16,8-24,3), movilidad (32,5; 28,6-36,5), reacción emocional (23,7; 20,4-27,1), sueño (33,8; 29,0-38,5) y aislamiento social (17,2; 14,3-20,1). El grado de deterioro global se asoció, de forma estadísticamente significativa, con mayor edad, convivencia fuera del núcleo familiar, mayor número de patologías crónicas, mayor consumo de fármacos y menor capacidad funcional. Conclusiones. Existe un grado de deterioro subjetivo importante en la calidad de vida del anciano frágil. Parece justificada la inclusión de la valoración de la calidad de vida subjetiva en la valoración integral de este tipo de pacientes.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Objective. To determine the subjective deterioration in quality of life in elderly people who met frailty criteria. Design. Cross-sectional, descriptive, observational study. Setting. Primary Care, Health Area Participants. Elderly people with signs of frailty. Exclusion criteria: frail elderly people who, due to their physical or mental impairment, were unable to complete the questionnaires or did not want to take part (total 8.5 %). Main measurements. Primary variable: Nottingham Health Profi le (NHP) quality of life questionnaire. Other variables were: socio-demographic data (age, gender and co-residence), number of chronic diseases, number of drugs being taken, and Barthels index for functional capacity. Results. The mean age of the participants was 81.4 years, 67.5% were women and 33.7% lived alone. The mean number of chronic diseases was 3.2 and the mean number of drugs being taken was 4.7. The percentage of overall deterioration on the NHP was 25.6 (95% CI 22.8-28.3), This percentage deterioration varied among the dimensions: energy (26.1; 21.2-31), pain (20.5; 16.8-24.3), physical mobility (32.5; 28.6-36.5), emotional reactions (23.7; 20.4-27.1), sleep (33.8; 29-38.5) and social isolation (17.2; 14.3-20.1). The degree of overall deterioration was associated, in a statistically signifi cant manner, with older age, co-residence outside the family, higher number of chronic diseases, higher number of drugs being taken and lower functional capacity. Conclusions. There is a signifi cant level of subjective deterioration in the quality of life in frail elderly people. Including the subjective evaluation of quality of life in the overall assessment of this type of patient would seem justified.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
