<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952013000100014</identifier>
<datestamp>2013-03-11</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Esparza-Martín,Noemí]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Hernández-Betancor,Araceli]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Suria-González,Santiago]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Batista-García,Fátima]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Braillard-Pocard,Pablo]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sánchez-Santana,Ana Y.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Guerra-Rodríguez,Rita]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ramírez-Puga,Ana]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Checa-Andrés,M. Dolores]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Nefropatía diabética]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hepatitis B]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hepatitis C]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[VIH]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Sífilis]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.33 n.1 2013]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2013-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952013000100014</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Serologías B, C, VIH y sífilis en la primera valoración de pacientes con diabetes remitidos a consulta externa de Nefrología]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Serology for Hepatitis B and C, HIV and syphilis in the initial evaluation of diabetes patients referred for an external Nephrology consultation]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Antecedentes: En España hay datos sobre prevalencia e incidencia de serologías microbiológicas positivas tanto en la población general como en pacientes en hemodiálisis. Sin embargo, se conocen pocos datos sobre los pacientes con diabetes atendidos en consulta externa de Nefrología. Objetivo: Valorar el porcentaje de pacientes con serologías positivas para hepatitis B y C, virus de inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH) y sífilis en la valoración inicial de los pacientes remitidos para estudio a la consulta externa de nefropatía diabética. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de las serologías solicitadas con el diagnóstico de nefropatía diabética con origen en consultas externas de 500 pacientes valorados durante 5 años a los que se les había solicitado serologías de la hepatitis B, C, VIH y sífilis. Resultados: Respecto al virus de la hepatitis B, el 0,4 % de los pacientes tenían hepatitis B crónica, el 10,2 % había pasado la hepatitis y estaban curados y el 4,2 % había recibido la vacuna de la hepatitis B. En cuanto a la hepatitis C, el 2,4 % de los pacientes estudiados tenían anticuerpos frente hepatitis C. Respecto a la sífilis, el 0,8 % de los pacientes tenían serologías positivas. Ningún paciente presentó serologías positivas para VIH. Conclusiones: Si bien con grandes limitaciones metodológicas, este sería el primer estudio donde se revisan las serologías microbiológicas de pacientes con nefropatía diabética atendidos en consulta externa.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Introduction: Information is available regarding the prevalence and incidence of positive microbiological serology results both in the general population and in patients on haemodialysis in Spain. Nevertheless, little information is known regarding patients with diabetes attended in external nephrology consultations. Objective: To evaluate the percentage of patients with positive serology results for hepatitis B and C, Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), and syphilis in the initial assessment of patients referred to diabetic nephropathy external consultations. Patients and method: Retrospective study of 500 patients assessed over the course of 5 years with the diagnosis of diabetic nephropathy originating in external consultations and for which hepatitis B, C, HIV, and syphilis serology had been requested. Results: With regard to hepatitis B virus, 0.4% of patients had chronic hepatitis B, 10.2% had overcome the hepatitis and were in recovery, and 4.2% had received the hepatitis B vaccine. As for hepatitis C, 2.4% of the patients studied had antibodies against hepatitis C. With regard to syphilis, 0.8% of patients had positive serological results. No patients had positive HIV serology results. Conclusions: Despite major methodological limitations, this would be the first study to evaluate the microbiological serology of diabetic nephropathy patients treated in external consultations.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
