<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952012000800010</identifier>
<datestamp>2013-01-21</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Fernández-Lucas,Milagros]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Teruel-Briones,José L.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Gomis-Couto,Antonio]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Villacorta-Pérez,Javier]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Quereda-Rodríguez-Navarro,Carlos]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hemodiálisis incremental]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Función renal residual en hemodiálisis]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Supervivencia]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.32 n.6 2012]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2012-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952012000800010</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Mantenimiento de la función renal residual en hemodiálisis: experiencia de 5 años de una pauta de diálisis incremental]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Maintaining residual renal function in patients on haemodialysis: 5-year experience using a progressively increasing dialysis regimen]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Introducción: A diferencia de los pacientes tratados con diálisis peritoneal, la programación de una dosis incremental de diálisis no se considera en el enfermo tratado con hemodiálisis (HD) periódica, ni tampoco es habitual tener en cuenta la función renal residual en el cálculo de la dosis total de diálisis, asumiéndose como tal la proporcionada exclusivamente por el aclaramiento del dializador. A partir del año 2006 decidimos establecer una pauta incremental de diálisis al inicio del tratamiento renal sustitutivo, valorando la posibilidad de comenzar con 2 HD/semana cuando el aclaramiento renal de urea fuera igual o superior a 2,5 ml/min. En el presente trabajo presentamos nuestra experiencia de los primeros 5 años de aplicación de esta pauta incremental de HD y su repercusión sobre la función renal residual. Metodología: Se han incluido a todos los enfermos que iniciaron tratamiento con HD periódica entre el 1/1/2006 y el 30/9/2010, y permanecieron en diálisis más de tres meses. El seguimiento de los enfermos finalizó el 31/12/2010 (fecha de cierre del estudio). Cuando un enfermo inicia HD se determina el aclaramiento de urea y creatinina con las concentraciones de urea y creatinina en una muestra de sangre obtenida antes de la diálisis y la orina de las 24 horas previas al inicio de la primera sesión de diálisis de la semana. Si el aclaramiento de urea es igual o superior a 2,5 ml/min, se comienza con 2 HD/semana, siempre que lo permita la situación clínica a criterio del médico responsable. La función renal residual se analiza cada dos meses hasta que la diuresis es inferior a 100 ml/día, que se considera nula. Evaluamos el descenso de la función renal residual, calculando el ritmo de descenso del filtrado glomerular (ml/min/mes) y de la diuresis de 24 horas (ml/mes) en los pacientes que se dializan con 2 y 3 HD a la semana. En enero de 2010 realizamos un corte transversal en el que se relacionó el filtrado glomerular con diversos parámetros clínicos y analíticos en pacientes que se dializan 2 y 3 veces a la semana. Resultados: En el período de estudio, se incluyeron 95 pacientes, de los cuales 41 (43%) empezaron con 2 HD y 54 (57%) con 3 HD a la semana. El tiempo medio que permanecieron con la pauta de 2 HD/semana fue de 11,1 ± 7,2 meses (rango 2-25). De los 41 enfermos que comenzaron con 2 HD/semana, 10 recibieron el trasplante mientras permanecían con esta pauta, 1 fue transferido a diálisis peritoneal, 6 recuperaron función renal y pudieron abandonar el tratamiento con diálisis, 15 pasaron a la pauta de 3 HD/semana y 9 continuaban dializándose con la pauta de 2 HD/semana en el momento de cierre del estudio. De los 15 enfermos que pasaron a la pauta de 3 HD/semana, 4 fueron trasplantados, 3 fallecieron y los 8 restantes continuaban en HD en la fecha de cierre del estudio. El análisis de Kaplan-Meyer mostró que la supervivencia de los pacientes que iniciaron 2 veces/semana fue mayor (log-rank 3,964, p = 0,04). La pérdida del filtrado glomerular y de la diuresis de 24 horas fue menor en los enfermos con la pauta de 2 HD/semana: 0,22 ± 0,36 vs. 0,89 ± 1,26 ml/min/mes para el filtrado glomerular (p = 0,001), y 90,59 ±132 vs. 206,23 ± 286 ml/mes para la diuresis de 24 horas (p = 0,001). En el corte transversal realizado en enero de 2010, 17 pacientes estaban con pauta de 2 HD/semana y 47 con 3 HD/semana. La concentración sérica de &#946;2-microglobulina fue significativamente menor en el grupo con 2 HD/semana (19,7 ± 5 vs. 38,3 ± 13, p = 0,000). La concentración media de hemoglobina fue similar en ambos grupos, con una dosis de eritropoyetina significativamente menor en los pacientes de 2 HD/semana (7058 ± 3749 vs. 12.553 ± 10.826 unidades/semana, p = 0,037). Conclusión: En una población seleccionada, el inicio de la HD se puede hacer de forma incremental, comenzando con dos sesiones de diálisis a la semana. En nuestra experiencia es una pauta segura que probablemente contribuye a preservar la función renal residual.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Introduction: In contrast to patients treated with peritoneal dialysis, those on periodical haemodialysis (HD) do not receive programmed progressive increases in dialysis dosage, nor is residual renal function taken into account in the calculation of the total dialysis prescription; rather, only dialyser clearance is factored into the equation. In 2006, we decided to establish a progressively increasing dialysis regimen at the start of renal replacement therapy, evaluating the possibility of starting with 2 sessions of HD/week when renal clearance of urea was equal to or greater than 2.5ml/min. This study summarises our experience during the first 5 years of application of this progressively increasing HD prescription and its repercussions on residual renal function. Methods: We included all patients who started periodical HD between 1/1/2006 and 30/9/2010 and remained on dialysis for more than three months. The follow-up period ended on 31/12/2010 (study end date). When a patient started HD, urea and creatinine clearance levels were measured based on urea and creatinine concentrations in blood samples taken before dialysis and in urine samples taken 24 hours prior to starting the first dialysis session of the week. If urea clearance was equal to or greater than 2.5ml/min, 2 sessions of HD per week were applied, as long as the patient's clinical situation allowed for it (according to the criteria of the attending physician). Residual renal function was analysed every 2 months until diuresis was less than 100ml/day, which is considered to be basically null. We evaluated the decrease in residual renal function, calculating the rate of decrease in glomerular filtration (ml/min/month) and 24-hour diuresis (ml/month) in patients receiving 2 and 3 HD sessions per week. In January 2010, we took a cross-sectional sample, evaluating glomerular filtration and how this value was associated with various clinical and laboratory parameters in patients receiving 2 or 3 dialysis sessions per week. Results: During the study period, 95 patients were included in the study, 41 of which (43%) started with 2 HD sessions per week, and 54 (57%) with 3 sessions per week. The mean time that patients remained on the 2HD sessions/week regimen was 11.1±7.2 months (range: 2-25 months). Of the 41 patients that started with 2 HD sessions/week, 10 received a transplant while on the treatment regimen, 1 was transferred to peritoneal dialysis, 6 recovered renal function and were able to abandon dialysis treatment, 15 were switched to the 3 HD sessions/week regimen, and 9 continued on the 2 HD sessions/week regimen at the time the study ended. Of the 15 patients that were switched to the 3 HD sessions/week regimen, 4 received transplants, 3 died, and the remaining 8 continued on HD until the end of the study. A Kaplan-Meier survival analysis revealed that patients who started on the 2 HD sessions/week regimen had a greater survival rate (log-rank: 3.964; P=.04). Loss in glomerular filtration rate and 24-hour diuresis were lower in patients on the 2 HD sessions/week regimen: 0.22±0.36ml/min/month vs 0.89±1.26ml/min/month for glomerular filtration (P=.001), and 90.59±132ml/month vs 206.23±286ml/month for 24-hour diuresis (P=.001). In the cross-sectional sample taken in January 2010, 17 patients were on the 2 HD sessions/week regimen and 47 were on the 3 HD sessions/week regimen. Serum concentrations of &#946;2-microglobulin were significantly lower in the 2 HD sessions/week group (19.7±5 vs 38.3±13; P=.000). The mean haemoglobin concentration was similar between the two groups, with a significantly lower dose required of erythropoietin in patients on the 2 HD sessions/week regimen (7058±3749 units/week vs 12 553±10 826 units/week; P=.037). Conclusion: In select populations, the start of HD can be administered on a progressively increasing dosage, starting with two sessions/week. In our experience, this is a safe prescription that probably contributes to preserving residual renal function.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
