<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952013000700003</identifier>
<datestamp>2014-01-08</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rosa-García,Estela de la]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Miramontes-Zapata,Mónica]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sánchez-Vargas,Luis O.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mondragón-Padilla,Arnoldo]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Candida albicans]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Candida glabrata]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Diabetes mellitus]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Albúmina sérica]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Enfermedad renal crónica]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hemodiálisis]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.33 n.6 2013]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2013-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952013000700003</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Colonización e infección bucal por Candida sp. en pacientes diabéticos y no diabéticos con enfermedad renal crónica en diálisis]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Oral colonisation and infection by Candida sp. in diabetic and non-diabetic patients with chronic kidney disease on dialysis]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Introducción: La candidosis bucal (CB) es una infección oportunista frecuente en el paciente inmunocomprometido y algunas veces es importante conocer la especie para el tratamiento. Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia de distintas especies de Candida colonizando o infectando la mucosa bucal (MB) de pacientes diabéticos (DM) y no diabéticos (no DM) con enfermedad renal crónica, comparando ambos grupos y explorando algunos posibles factores de riesgo. Metodología: Se examinó a 56 pacientes DM y 80 no DM con diálisis crónica. Se tomaron muestras de la MB y se sembraron en agar placas dextrosa Sabouraud. La especie se identificó con galerías API®. La CB se confirmó con citología exfoliativa. Las asociaciones se investigaron con &#967;², Prueva exacta (PE) de Fisher y regresión logística múltiple. Resultados: La prevalencia de Candida fue del 43,4 %: 53,6 % DM y 36,2 % no DM (p = 0,045). Las especies fueron C. albicans 74,6 %, C. glabrata 22,0 %, C. tropicalis 15,2 %, C. parapsilosis 3,4 %, C. kefyr 3,4 % y C. famata 1,7 % sin diferencia entre grupos. Los DM tuvieron mayor frecuencia de xerostomía (p = 0,002), flujo salival bajo (p = 0,008) y albúmina sérica más baja (p = 0,018). Tuvieron CB 16,9 %, 23,2 % DM frente a 12,5 % no DM (p = 0,101). Se asociaron a presencia de Candida en la MB: uso de prótesis (odds ratio [OR] 25,6, límite de confianza [LC] 95 % 2,5 a 253, p = 0,001), xerostomía (OR 9,6, LC 95 % 2,4 a 38,1, p = 0,001) y bajos valores de albúmina sérica (OR 0,41, LC 95 % 0,22 a 0,98, p = 0,044). Conclusiones: La presencia de Candida sp. en la MB se asoció a prótesis dental, xerostomía y albúmina sérica baja.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Introduction: Oral candidiasis (OC) is a common opportunistic infection in immunocompromised patients. Species identification is sometimes important for treatment. Objective: to determine the prevalence of different Candida species colonising or infecting the oral mucosa (OM) of diabetic (DM) and non-diabetic (non-DM) chronic kidney disease patients, comparing both groups and exploring potential risk factors. Methods: 56 DM and 80 non-DM patients on chronic dialysis were examined. OM swabs were cultured on Sabouraud dextrose agar plates. Candida species were identified with API® galleries. OC was confirmed by exfoliative cytology. Statistical associations were analysed using &#967;2, Fisher's exact test (ET), and multiple logistic regression. Results: Candida prevalence was 43.4%: 53.6% DM and 36.3% non-DM, (p=.045). The species identified were C. albicans 74.6%, C. glabrata 22.0%, C. tropicalis 15.2%, C. parapsilosis 3.4 %, C. kefyr 3.4% and C. famata 1.7% without difference between groups. DM patients had a higher xerostomia prevalence (p=.002) and lower salivary flow (p=.008) and lower serum albumin (p=.018). 16.9% of patients had OC, 23.2% DM compared with 12.5% non-DM, (p=.101). The following were associated with the presence of Candida in the OM: the use of dental prostheses (odds ratio [OR] 25.6, 95% confidence interval [CI] 2.5 to 253, P=.001), xerostomia (OR 9.6, 95% CI 2.4 to 38.1, P=.001) and low serum albumin values (OR 0.41, 95% CI 0.22 to 0.98, P=.044). Conclusions: The presence of Candida sp. in the OM was associated with dental prostheses, xerostomia and low serum albumin.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
