<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952012000800009</identifier>
<datestamp>2013-01-21</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Frutos-Sanz,Miguel Á.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Guerrero-Gómez,Francisco]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Daga-Ruiz,Domingo]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cabello-Díaz,Mercedes]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lebrón-Gallardo,Miguel]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Quesada-García,Guillermo]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ruiz-Valverde,Andrés]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Baena-González,Víctor]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Hernández-Marrero,Domingo]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Donación en asistolia]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Donante en parada cardíaca]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Donante con criterios expandidos]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Trasplante renal de riñones en asistolia]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.32 n.6 2012]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2012-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952012000800009</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Trasplante renal con injertos procedentes de donantes en parada cardíaca Maastricht tipo III]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Kidney transplantation with grafts from type III Maastricht non-beating-heart donors]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[El trasplante renal (TR) con riñones de donantes fallecidos en parada cardíaca (PC) está creciendo en nuestro país. La mayoría procede de donantes con los criterios de Maastricht tipo II, si bien en los últimos años el donante fallecido tras limitación de tratamientos de soporte vital (LTSV) es una realidad en algunos países europeos y norteamericanos y constituye el Maastricht tipo III. Se presenta una serie de 6 TR con riñones de donantes fallecidos tras PC como consecuencia de LTSV en tres hospitales del Sector Málaga. Tras consensuar protocolo de actuación en el que la valoración como donante fue siempre posterior a la decisión de LTSV, se planteó a las familias la opción de donación. La preservación de los riñones se realizó mediante sonda de doble balón tipo Porges que se colocó antes de la PC. En dos casos la LTSV se realizó en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos y en el tercero en quirófano. Los tiempos desde inicio LTSV hasta la PC oscilaron entre 15 y 40 minutos, con un tiempo de parada circulatoria antes del inicio de la perfusión entre 5 y 11 minutos. La perfusión-enfriamiento de los riñones se realizó inicialmente con solución salina y posteriormente con solución preservadora de órganos (Celsior o Belzer) para a continuación proceder a la extracción renal con técnica quirúrgica rápida. Los tiempos de isquemia caliente verdadera o funcional fueron de 60, 59 y 50 minutos respectivamente para cada uno de los tres donantes. La validación de los riñones se produjo tras valorar tiempos totales del procedimiento (incluida la hipotensión previa a la PC), macroscopia renal y anatomía patológica de una cuña extraída a cada riñón. Los trasplantados con estos 6 riñones dieron su consentimiento para recibir riñones de donante expandido. La isquemia fría osciló entre 9 y 20 horas (media: 14,6 horas). Uno de los receptores presentó complicaciones hemorrágicas en el posoperatorio inmediato que precisó trasplantectomía. Los otros cinco mantienen los injertos funcionantes en la actualidad. Todos presentaron retraso funcional del injerto y necesitaron hemodiálisis. El rango del filtrado glomerular estimado en la última revisión se encuentra entre 23,0 y 106 ml/min/1,73 m². Como conclusión de esta experiencia, los donantes Maastricht tipo III proporcionan riñones válidos para trasplante, aunque esta serie muestra que la isquemia caliente funcional soportada fue importante, consecuencia del daño isquémico acumulado desde la fase agónica, la parada circulatoria y la preservación con soluciones frías. Por ello, mejorar la calidad de los resultados de los trasplantes renales realizados con este tipo de donantes pasa por una cuidadosa selección de donantes y acortar los tiempos de isquemia funcional total.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Kidney transplantation (KT) with kidneys from non-beating-heart donors (NBHD) is a growing trend in Spain. The majority of these kidneys come from type II Maastricht patients, although in recent years, organ donations from patients deceased due to cardiac arrest following limitation of life-sustaining therapy has already been in practice in certain European and North American countries, and it involves type III Maastricht patients. We present a series of 6 KT using kidneys from NHBD as a consequence of limitation of life-sustaining therapy in three different hospitals in the sector of Malaga. After agreeing upon a protocol for evaluating the potential of a patient for organ donation, which was always after deciding to limit life-sustaining therapy, the patients' families were given the option of organ donation. Kidneys were preserved using a Porges double balloon catheter, which was placed prior to cardiac arrest. In two cases, the limitation of life-sustaining therapy took place in the intensive care unit, and in the third case, in the operating room. The interval between limitation of life-sustaining therapy and cardiac arrest ranged between 15 minutes and 40 minutes, with an interval of circulatory arrest prior to perfusion of 5-11 minutes. Perfusion-cooling of the kidneys was initially carried out using saline solution, followed by organ preservation solution (Celsior or Belzer) and extraction of the kidney using a rapid surgical technique. True or functional hot ischaemia times were 60 minutes, 59 minutes, and 50 minutes, respectively, for each of the three donors. Kidneys were evaluated for viability using time intervals for the procedure (including hypotension prior to cardiac arrest), macroscopic appearance, and histopathology of a sample taken from each kidney. The recipients of these 6 kidneys had given their consent to receive organs from expanded-criteria donors. Cold ischaemia lasted between 9 hours and 20 hours (mean: 14.6 hours). One recipient developed haemorrhagic complications during the immediate postoperative period and required a transplantectomy. The other five currently retain functioning grafts. All had delayed graft function and needed haemodialysis. The range of estimated glomerular filtration rates at the most recent follow-up evaluation was 23.0-106ml/min/1.73m². In conclusion, type III Maastricht donors provide valid kidneys for transplantation, although this series showed that supported functional hot ischaemia was very important, the consequence of accumulated ischaemic damage starting in the agonal phase, circulatory arrest, and organ preservation using cold solutions. As such, to improve the quality of results obtained using kidneys from these types of donors would involve a very careful selection of optimal donors and minimisation of total functional ischaemia times.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
