<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952014000300008</identifier>
<datestamp>2014-07-31</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[González-Casaus,M. Luisa]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[González-Parra,Emilio]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sánchez-González,Carmen]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Albalate,Marta]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Piedra-Gordo,Concepción de la]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Fernández,Elvira]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Torregrosa,Vicente]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rodríguez,Mariano]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lorenzo,Víctor]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Parathormona]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Diálisis peritoneal]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hueso adinámico]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Metabolismo mineral y óseo]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Determinación de PTH]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.34 n.3 2014]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2014-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952014000300008</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[La menor proporción de parathormona circulante biológicamente activa en diálisis peritoneal no permite el ajuste intermétodo de parathormona establecida para hemodiálisis]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[A lower proportion of circulating active parathyroid hormone in peritoneal dialysis does not allow the pth inter-method adjustment proposed for haemodialysis]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Introducción: la parathormona (PTH) presenta buena correlación con los parámetros histomorfométricos y bioquímicos de remodelado óseo, aunque su cuantificación presenta limitaciones por la variabilidad según el método empleado. La PTH circulante es una mezcla de péptidos, y solo la PTH 1-84 es responsable de su actividad. Los fragmentos carboxiterminales tienen acción antagónica y, al aclararse por el riñón, varía su proporción según el estadio de enfermedad renal crónica. Nos planteamos estudiar posibles diferencias en su proporción en función del tipo de diálisis: hemodiálisis (HD) o diálisis peritoneal (DP). Material y métodos: En 73 pacientes en DP (46 varones y 27 mujeres entre 22 y 82 años) se cuantificó calcio total (Ca) y iónico (Cai), fosforo (P), telopéptidos carboxiterminales del colágeno tipo I (BCTx) y PTH mediante seis métodos de segunda generación (uno isotópico (IRMA) y cinco inmunoquimioluminescentes (ECLIA) y por el único método PTH de tercera generación (IRMA) disponible en ese momento. Resultados: Las concentraciones medias de Ca, Cai, P y BCTx fueron respectivamente, 9.03, 4.76, 4.73 mg/dl y 1181 pmol/l. Se observaron diferencias significativas en la PTH dependiendo del método de segunda generación utilizado. Los valores de PTH ajustados al rango equivalente a 150-300 de la PTH Allegro de Nichols en los pacientes en DP fueron superiores a los obtenidos en el estudio previo de HD. El porcentaje de PTH 1-84 biológicamente activa y el ratio PTH 1-84/7-84 fueron significativamente menores, indicando que, a igualdad de valor de PTH intacta, el porcentaje de fragmentos 7-84 circulantes es mayor en los pacientes en DP. Conclusión: Los pacientes en DP tienen una mayor proporción de fragmentos 7-84 PTH. Por este motivo las fórmulas de corrección inter-método utilizadas en los pacientes en HD no son aplicables en DP. En este estudio sugerimos otras fórmulas para aplicar en DP.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Introduction: Parathyroid hormone (PTH) shows a strong correlation with histomorphometric and biochemical parameters of bone turnover, however its measurement presents limitations due to inter-method variability. Circulating PTH is a mixture of peptides, but only on its whole form (1-84 PTH) is responsible of PTH biological activity. Carboxyl-terminal fragments exhibit antagonist actions and their proportion differs at each stage of chronic kidney disease, as consequence of differences on their renal clearance. The aim of this study is to evaluate possible differences in the proportion of these fragments according to dialysis type: haemodialysis (HD) or peritoneal dialysis (PD). Material and methods: Serum total (Ca) and ionized calcium (iCa), phosphate (P), carboxyl-terminal telopeptides of collagen type I (BCTx) were measured in 73 patients on PD (46 men and 27 women with an age between 22 and 82 years). PTH was quantified by six second generation assays (one isotopic and five chemiluminescence assays) and by one third generation PTH method. Results: Mean serum levels of Ca, iCa, P and BCTx were 9.03, 4.76, 4.73 mg/dl and 1181 pmol/l, respectively. Significant differences were observed in PTH values according to the method used. Adjustment of PTH results to PTH Allegro (Nichols) range of 150-300 nmol/l in PD patients showed higher values than those assessed previously for HD population. The percentage of biologically active 1-84 PTH as the 1-84 PTH/ 7-84 PTH ratio in PD were significantly lower than in HD patients, reflecting the higher proportion of 7-84 PTH circulating fragments for a given intact PTH result in PD. Conclusions: PD patients have a higher proportion of 7-84 PTH circulating fragments. Consequently, the inter-method adjustment algorithms proposed for HD patients are not useful for PD patients. This study proposes alternative algorithms for PTH inter-method adjustment to be applied in PD.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
