<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952009000600009</identifier>
<datestamp>2010-03-10</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[García Martos,P.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Gil de Sola,F.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marín,P.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[García-Agudo,L.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[García-Agudo,R.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tejuca,F.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Calle,L.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Peritonitis]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Peritonitis fúngica]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Diálisis peritoneal]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Candida]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Fluconazol]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.29 n.6 2009]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2009-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952009000600009</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Peritonitis fúngica en diálisis peritoneal continua ambulatoria: descripción de 10 casos]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Fungal peritonitis in continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis: report of 10 cases]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Antecedentes: La peritonitis fúngica es una complicación infrecuente pero grave en pacientes en diálisis peritoneal continua ambulatoria (DPCA). Métodos: Durante un período de 10 años (1999-2008), de un total de 175 pacientes con insuficiencia renal crónica en tratamiento con DPCA, estudiamos retrospectivamente 10 casos de peritonitis fúngica, analizando los factores predisponentes, aspectos clínicos, agentes etiológicos y tratamiento. El diagnóstico se estableció por la presencia de efluente peritoneal turbio con recuento superior a 100 leucocitos/µl y aislamiento de hongos en el cultivo microbiológico. Resultados: La peritonitis fúngica representó un 3,6% del total de peritonitis. Nueve pacientes tenían historia de peritonitis bacteriana previa y todos habían recibido antibioterapia. Otros hallazgos destacables fueron: edad superior a 70 años (50%) y diabetes mellitus (40%). El examen microscópico del líquido peritoneal fue de utilidad para sospechar la infección en 6 pacientes (60%). Los agentes responsables de peritonitis fueron: Candida parapsilosis (4), C. albicans (2), C. tropicalis (1), C. glabrata (1), C. famata (1) y Fusarium oxysporum (1). Los antifúngicos utilizados en el tratamiento fueron: fluconazol intraperitoneal y oral, vorizonazol intravenoso y oral y anfotericina B intravenosa. A consecuencia de la infección fúngica, 8 pacientes fueron transferidos a hemodiálisis. Un paciente murió antes de ser diagnosticado y otros tres durante el episodio de peritonitis. Conclusiones: Los pacientes con episodios de peritonitis bacteriana previos y tratamiento antibiótico presentaron un mayor riesgo de desarrollar peritonitis fúngica. C. parapsilosis fue el patógeno más frecuente. El tratamiento antifúngico junto con la retirada del catéter peritoneal fue eficaz en el 60% de los pacientes.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Background: Fungal peritonitis is a rare but serious complication in patients undergoing continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis (CAPD). Methods: During a ten-year period (1999-2008), from a total of 175 patients with chronic renal failure undergoing CAPD, we retrospectively studied 10 cases of fungal peritonitis analyzing the predisposing factors, clinical aspects, etiological agents and treatment. Diagnosis was based on elevated CAPD effluent count (>100/µl) and isolation of fungi on culture. Results: Fungal peritonitis represented 3.6% of all peritonitis episodes. Nine patients had a history of previous bacterial peritonitis and all of them were under antibiotic therapy. Other common findings were: age higher than 70 years old (50%) and diabetes mellitus (40%). Direct microscopic examination of the peritoneal fluid was useful for the suspicion of fungal infection in six patients (60%). The responsible agents for peritonitis were: Candida parapsilosis (4), C. albicans (2), C. tropicalis (1), C. glabrata (1), C. famata (1) and Fusarium oxysporum (1). Intraperitoneal and oral fluconazole, intravenous and oral voriconazole and intravenous amphotericin B were the antifungal agents used in the treatment. As a result of fungal infection, eight patients were transferred to hemodialysis. One patient died before the diagnosis and three other during the episode of peritonitis. Conclusions: Patients with previous bacterial peritonitis and antibiotic treatment were at greater risk of developing fungal peritonitis. C. parapsilosis was the most common pathogen. For the successful management of fungal peritonitis besides the antifungal therapy, peritoneal catheter removal was necessary in 60% of patients.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
