<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952014000800001</identifier>
<datestamp>2014-12-15</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Górriz,José L.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Gutiérrez,Félix]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Trullas,Joan C.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arazo,Piedad]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arribas,José R.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Barril,Guillermina]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cervero,Miguel]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cofan,Frederic]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Domingo,Pere]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Estrada,Vicente]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Fulladosa,Xavier]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Galindo,María J.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Gràcia,Silvia]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Iribarren,José A.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Knobel,Hernando]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[López-Aldeguer,José]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lozano,Fernando]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Martínez-Castelao,Alberto]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Martínez,Esteban]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mazuecos,María A.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Miralles,Celia]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Montañés,Rosario]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Negredo,Eugenia]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Palacios,Rosario]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pérez-Elías,María J.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Portilla,Joaquín]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Praga,Manuel]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Quereda,Carlos]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rivero,Antonio]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Santamaría,Juan M.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sanz,José]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sanz,Jesús]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Miró,José M.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Sida]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[VIH]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Enfermedad renal crónica]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Función renal]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Insuficiencia renal]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Tenofovir]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Toxicidad renal]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Fármacos antirretrovirales]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Trasplante renal]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.34 suppl.2 2014]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2014-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952014000800001</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Documento de consenso sobre el manejo de la patología renal en pacientes con infección por VIH]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Consensus document on the evaluation and management of renal disease in HIV-infected patients]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Objetivo: Actualizar las recomendaciones sobre la evaluación y el manejo de la afectación renal en pacientes con infección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH). Métodos: Este documento ha sido consensuado por un panel de expertos del Grupo de Estudio de Sida (GESIDA) de la Sociedad Española de Enfermedades Infecciosas y Microbiología Clínica (SEIMC), de la Sociedad Española de Nefrología (S.E.N.) y de la Sociedad Española de Química Clínica y Patología Molecular (SEQC). Para la valoración de la calidad de la evidencia y la graduación de las recomendaciones se ha utilizado el sistema Grading of Recommendations Assessment, Development and Evaluation (GRADE). Resultados: La evaluación renal debe incluir la medida de la concentración sérica de creatinina, la estimación del filtrado glomerular (ecuación chronic kidney disease epidemiological collaboration [CKD-EPI]), la medida del cociente proteína/creatinina en orina y un sedimento urinario. El estudio básico de la función tubular ha de incluir la concentración sérica de fosfato y la tira reactiva de orina (glucosuria). En ausencia de alteraciones, el cribado será anual. En pacientes tratados con tenofovir o con factores de riesgo para el desarrollo de enfermedad renal crónica (ERC), se recomienda una evaluación más frecuente. Se debe evitar el uso de antirretrovirales potencialmente nefrotóxicos en pacientes con ERC o factores de riesgo para evitar su progresión. En este documento se revisan las indicaciones de derivación del paciente a Nefrología y las de la biopsia renal, así como las indicaciones y la evaluación y el manejo del paciente en diálisis o del trasplante renal. Conclusiones: La función renal debe monitorizarse en todos los pacientes con infección por el VIH y este documento pretende optimizar la evaluación y el manejo de la afectación renal.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Objective: To update the 2010 recommendations on the evaluation and management of renal disease in HIV-infected patients. Methods: This document was approved by a panel of experts from the AIDS Working Group (GESIDA) of the Spanish Society of Infectious Diseases and Clinical Microbiology (SEIMC), the Spanish Society of Nephrology (S.E.N.), and the Spanish Society of Clinical Chemistry and Molecular Pathology (SEQC). The quality of evidence and the level of recommendation were evaluated using the Grading of Recommendations Assessment, Development and Evaluation (GRADE) system. Results: The basic renal work-up should include measurements of serum creatinine, estimated glomerular filtration rate by CKD-EPI, Urine protein-to-creatinine ratio, and urinary sediment. Tubular function tests should include determination of serum phosphate levels and urine dipstick for glucosuria. In the absence of abnormal values, renal screening should be performed annually. In patients treated with tenofovir or with risk factors for chronic kidney disease (CKD), more frequent renal screening is recommended. In order to prevent disease progression, potentially nephrotoxic antiretroviral drugs are not recommended in patients with CKD or risk factors for CKD. The document advises on the optimal time for referral of a patient to the nephrologist and provides indications for renal biopsy. The indications for and evaluation and management of dialysis and renal transplantation are also addressed. Conclusions: Renal function should be monitored in all HIV-infected patients. The information provided in this document should enable clinicians to optimize the evaluation and management of HIV-infected patients with renal disease.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
