<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0212-97282016000200004</identifier>
<datestamp>2016-06-14</datestamp>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Barriopedro,Maria I.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ruiz-Pérez,Luis M.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Gómez-Ruano,Miguel A.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rico,Isabel]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Interacción social]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Medición de la invarianza]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Análisis factorial confirmatorio]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Educación física]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Profesorado]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Universidad de Murcia]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Anales de Psicología  v.32 n.2 2016]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2016-05-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0212-97282016000200004</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Las preferencias participativas del profesorado de educación física en su actividad profesional]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The physical education teachers' participative preferences in their professional activity]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Los entornos colaborativos han sido promocionados como la mejor solución a los problemas que la actividad docente puede presentar independientemente de las preferencias personales de los profesores. El objetivo del estudio es desarrollar una escala de preferencias de interacción social en el entorno laboral para los profesores de educación física, partiendo de la Escala GR de Ruiz et al. (2010), así como evaluar su equivalencia de medida en profesores con diferentes años de experiencia docente y entre hombres y mujeres, utilizando el análisis factorial confirmatorio multigrupo. En este estudio participaron 1413 profesores españoles. La escala final quedó constituida por las 4 cuatro dimensiones originarias: Cooperación, Competición, Individualismo y Afiliación que explicaron un 66.43% de la varianza y presentaron valores elevados de consistencia interna. Por otro lado, los resultados indican una equivalencia factorial estricta. Los profesores con más años de experiencia prefieren escenarios de trabajo más individualistas y cooperativos que aquellos con menor experiencia y los hombres tienen preferencias más individualistas y competitivas, mientras que las mujeres tienen mayor orientación cooperativa.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Nowadays the collaborative learning environments have been promoted by the physical education teachers as the best way for decreasing teaching problems independently of teachers' personal achievements. The aim of the present study was to develop a scale for physical education teachers about social interactions preferences in the workplace environment. Based on the scale GR developed by Ruiz et al. (2010), the multisample confirmatory factor analysis was used to assess the equivalence measure between years of experience and gender. The participants were 1413 Spanish physical education teachers. The final scale was composed of the 4 initial dimensions: cooperation, competition, individualization, and affiliation. The four dimensions accounted for 66.43% of the total variance, and showed high values of internal consistency. Also, the results pointed out a strict factorial invariance. Finally, the results showed that the more experienced teachers prefer individualized and competitive workplace environments than the less experienced ones, and on the other hand, men's teachers were more individualistic and competitive compared with women's teachers whom prefer cooperative orientations in the workplace environment.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
