<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952013000100005</identifier>
<datestamp>2013-03-11</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Górriz,José L.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Molina,Pablo]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Bover,Jordi]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Barril,Guillermina]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Martín-de Francisco,Ángel L.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caravaca,Francisco]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Hervás,José]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Piñera,Celestino]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Escudero,Verónica]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Molinero,Luis M.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Guías K/DOQI]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Colecalciferol]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Enfermedad renal crónica]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hormona paratiroidea]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Metabolismo óseo-mineral]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Fósforo]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Calcitriol]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Vitamina D]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.33 n.1 2013]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2013-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952013000100005</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Características del metabolismo óseo y mineral en pacientes con enfermedad renal crónica en estadios 3-5 no en diálisis: resultados del estudio OSERCE]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Characteristics of bone mineral metabolism in patients with stage 3-5 chronic kidney disease not on dialysis: results of the OSERCE study]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[OSERCE es un estudio multicéntrico y transversal cuyo objetivo es conocer las características bioquímicas, clínicas y el manejo de las alteraciones del metabolismo óseo-mineral, así como el grado de cumplimiento de las guías K/DOQI en pacientes con enfermedad renal crónica (ERC) no en diálisis. Se incluyeron 634 pacientes procedentes de 32 Unidades de Nefrología de España con ERC no en diálisis y filtrado glomerular < 60 ml/min/1,73 m² (estadios K/DOQI: 33 % estadio 3 , 46 % estadio 4 y 21 % estadio 5 no en diálisis). En 409 pacientes se realizó además analítica en un laboratorio centralizado determinando creatinina, calcio, fósforo, hormona paratiroidea (PTH) intacta, 25 OH vitamina D y 1,25 OH2 vitamina D. El porcentaje de incumplimiento en los objetivos establecidos por las guías K/DOQI para niveles de calcio, fósforo, PTH intacta y producto calcio x fósforo fue 45 %, 22 %, 70 % y 4 % respectivamente. El 70% de los pacientes presentaban los niveles de PTH intacta fuera del rango establecido por las guías K/DOQI (55,5 % con valores por encima del límite superior y 14,5 % por debajo del límite inferior). El 45 % de los pacientes presentaban niveles de calcio fuera de rango (40 % por encima y 5 % por debajo del rango), mientras que el 22 % presentaron niveles inadecuados de fósforo (3 % por debajo del objetivo y 19 % por encima). El 4 % de los pacientes presentaron niveles de producto calcio x fósforo fuera de rango. Solo el 1,8 % de los pacientes cumplieron los cuatro objetivos K/DOQI. Los valores detectados en la analítica centralizada no mostraron diferencia respecto a los de la analítica general. El 81,5 % de los pacientes presentaba deficiencia de calcidiol (25 OH D3) (< 30 ng/ml). El 35 % presentaron insuficiencia moderada-grave (< 15 ng/ml), y el 47 % insuficiencia leve (15-30 ng/ml). El 64,7 % presentaron insuficiencia de calcitriol (1,25 OH2 D3 < 22 pg/ml). Mientras que el déficit de calcidiol no se relacionó con los estadios de ERC, la deficiencia de calcitriol fue más pronunciada conforme avanzó el estadio de ERC. Los resultados del estudio OSERCE confirman la dificultad de conseguir los niveles objetivo establecidos por las guías K/DOQI en la ERC no en diálisis, fundamentalmente en el pobre control del hiperparatiroidismo secundario y del déficit de vitamina D. Por ello es necesario revisar las estrategias de abordaje del tratamiento de las alteraciones del metabolismo óseo-mineral en estos pacientes, y quizá una revisión de los parámetros objetivo de las guías actuales.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[OSERCE is a multi-centre and cross-sectional study with the aim of analysing the biochemical, clinical, and management characteristics of bone mineral metabolism alterations and the level of compliance with K/DOQI guideline recommendations in patients with chronic kidney disease (CKD) not on dialysis. The study included a total of 634 patients from 32 different Spanish nephrology units, all with CKD, estimated glomerular filtration rates <60ml/min/1.73m², and not on dialysis (K/DOQI stage: 33% stage 3, 46% stage 4, and 21% stage 5). In 409 of these patients, laboratory parameters were also measured in a centralised laboratory, including creatinine, calcium, phosphorous, intact parathyroid hormone (PTH), 25-OH-vitamin D, and 1,25-OH2-Vitamin D levels. The rates of non-compliance with the K/DOQI objectives for calcium, phosphorous, intact PTH, and calcium x phosphate product among these patients were 45%, 22%, 70%, and 4%, respectively. Of the 70% of patients with intact PTH levels outside of the target range established by the K/DOQI guidelines, 55.5% had values above the upper limit and 14.5% had values below the lower limit. Of the 45% of patients with calcium levels outside of the target range, 40% had values above the upper limit and 5% had values below the lower limit. Of the 22% of patients with phosphorous levels outside of the target range, 19% had values above the upper limit, and 3% had values below the lower limit. Finally, 4% of patients also had values for the calcium x phosphate product that were outside of the recommended range. Only 1.8% of patients complied with all four K/DOQI objectives. The values detected in centralised laboratory analyses were not significantly different from those measured in the laboratories at each institution. In addition, 81.5% of patients had a deficiency of calcidiol (25-OH-D3) (<30ng/ml); of these, 35% had moderate-severe deficiency (<15ng/ml) and 47% had mild deficiency (15-30ng/ml). Calcitriol (1,25-OH2-D3) levels were deficient in 64.7% of patients. Whereas the calcidiol deficiency was not correlated with the CKD stage, calcitriol deficit were more pronounced at more advanced stages of CKD. The results of the OSERCE study confirm the difficulty in reaching the target values recommended by the K/DOQI guidelines in patients with CKD not on dialysis, in particular in the form of poor control of secondary hyperparathyroidism and vitamin D deficiency. With this in mind, we must review strategies for treating bone mineral metabolism alterations in these patients, and perhaps revise the target parameters set by current guidelines.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
