<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952013000200006</identifier>
<datestamp>2013-04-23</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[García-Agudo,Rebeca]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Aoufi-Rabih,Sami]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Barril-Cuadrado,Guillermina]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hepatitis C]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hemodiálisis]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Enfermedad renal crónica]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.33 n.2 2013]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2013-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952013000200006</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Estudio multicéntrico español SHECTS: situación hepática de los pacientes con hepatitis crónica por el VHC en tratamiento sustitutivo renal con hemodiálisis]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[SHECTS multi-centre Spanish study: liver situation of patients with chronic hepatitis from HCV on renal replacement therapy with haemodialysis]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Introducción: La hepatitis C crónica en pacientes en diálisis es mayor que en la población general. El estudio SHECTS, tiene como objetivos analizar el nivel de estudio y seguimiento de los pacientes con infección crónica por el virus de la hepatitis C (VHC) en hemodiálisis y determinar su prevalencia actual. Método: Estudio de cohorte multicéntrico nacional, realizado entre septiembre de 2010 y septiembre de 2011. Se envió un cuaderno de recogida de datos a todas las unidades de hemodiálisis de España para incluir información de la unidad y de la situación nefrológica y hepatológica de sus pacientes VHC-positivos. Resultados: Participaron en el estudio 187 unidades de hemodiálisis (71 hospitalarias). La prevalencia del VHC se estimó en el 5,6 %. La causa más frecuente de enfermedad renal crónica fue la glomerular (25 %); del 72,1% de los pacientes que se había sometido a una biopsia renal, el 23,2 % presentaba una glomerulonefritis que podía estar asociada al VHC. No se siponía del genotipo en el 64 %, ecografía hepática en el 61,3 %, biopsia hepática en el 87,7 %. Un tercio era seguido por un digestólogo. El 26,6 % había recibido tratamiento antiviral, con respuesta viral sostenida en el 35,3 % y suspensión del tratamiento en el 67,4 %. Conclusión: La prevalencia del VHC en hemodiálisis en España ha disminuido notablemente en la última década hasta igualarse a la de países del entorno. Estos pacientes tienen un estudio incompleto de su hepatopatía y los tributarios de tratamiento antiviral y no tratados constituyen un número considerable, a pesar de tener cargas virales bajas y ser candidatos a trasplante renal.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Introduction: Chronic hepatitis C in dialysis patients is higher than in the general population. The SHECTS study has the goal of analysing the level of examination and follow-up of patients with chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV) infections on haemodialysis, and to determine the current prevalence of these patients. Method: A national, multicentre, cohort study carried out between September 2010 and September 2011. We sent a data collection folder to all Spanish haemodialysis units to include information regarding each centre and the nephrological/hepatological situation of their HCV-positive patients. Results: A total of 187 haemodialysis units (71 hospital-based) participated in the study. The global prevalence of HCV was estimated at 5.6%. The most common cause of chronic kidney disease was glomerular (25%); of the 72.1% of patients who had undergone a renal biopsy, 23.2% had glomerulonephritis that could have been associated with HCV. Genotyping had not been carried out in 64%, liver ultrasound had not been applied in 61.3%, and liver biopsies were not performed in 87.7%. One-third of all patients received care from a gastroenterologist. Antiviral treatment was administered to 26.6% of patients, with a sustained viral response in 35.3% and suspension of treatment in 67.4%. Conclusion: The prevalence of HCV in patients on haemodialysis in Spain has decreased considerably in the last decade to the point of reaching similar rates to those of neighbouring countries. These patients receive incomplete analyses of liver condition, and individuals who receive antiviral treatment and untreated patients constitute a large proportion, despite having low viral loads and being candidates for kidney transplants.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
