<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952015000400006</identifier>
<datestamp>2016-03-02</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Esteve Simo,Vicent]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Junqué Jiménez,Anna]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Moreno Guzmán,Fátima]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Carneiro Oliveira,José]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Fulquet Nicolas,Miquel]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pou Potau,Mónica]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Saurina Sole,Anna]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Duarte Gallego,Verónica]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tapia Gonzalez,Irati]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ramirez de Arellano,Manel]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Ejercicio]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Anciano]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hemodiálisis]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.35 n.4 2015]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2015-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952015000400006</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Beneficios del ejercicio físico de baja intensidad durante la sesión de hemodiálisis en el paciente anciano]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Benefits of a low intensity exercise programme during haemodialysis sessions in elderly patients]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Introducción: Los pacientes ancianos constituyen un grupo en continuo crecimiento en los programas de hemodiálisis (HD). Estos se caracterizan por su elevada complejidad, dependencia y comorbilidad asociada. Múltiples beneficios del ejercicio físico en los pacientes en HD han sido descritos, si bien no han sido completamente evaluados en la población anciana. Objetivos: Analizar el efecto de un programa adaptado de ejercicio físico intradiálisis sobre la fuerza muscular, la capacidad funcional y la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud en nuestros pacientes ancianos (&gt;80 años) en HD. Material y métodos: Estudio prospectivo unicéntrico no aleatorizado (12 semanas) con 2 grupos comparativos. El grupo ejercicio (E) incluía un programa de ejercicio físico adaptado mediante pelotas medicinales, pesas, bandas elásticas y cicloergómetros en las primeras 2 h de HD. El grupo control (C) recibía el cuidado habitual en HD. Analizamos: 1) Parámetros bioquímicos. 2) Fuerza de extensión máxima de cuádriceps (FEMQ) y "hand-grip" (HG). 3) Tests de capacidad funcional: "sit to stand to sit" (STS10) y "six-minutes walking test" (6MWT). 4) Sintomatología depresiva: inventario Beck (BDI). 5) Calidad de vida: EuroQol-5D (EQ-5D). Resultados: Un total de 22 pacientes incluidos: 50% hombres. Edad media 83,2 años y 44,1 meses en HD. Charlson medio: 9,5. Principal etiología: DM (36,4%). Un total de 11 pacientes asignados al grupo E y 11 al grupo C. No se observaron efectos adversos relacionados. Al final del estudio, el grupo E presentó de forma global una mejoría en las pruebas realizadas (*p < 0,05): FEMQ 10,5 ± 7,6 vs. 12,9 ± 10,1 kg; HG* 16,6 ± 8,7 vs. 18,2 ± 8,9 kg; STS10* 29,9 ± 10,6 vs. 25 ± 7,87 sec; 6MWT* 14,6%, 234,4 vs. 274,7 m; BDI* 14,4 ± 11,5 vs. 11,7 ± 10,8 y EQ-5D 49 ± 19,1 vs. 59,5 ± 20,3. Estos cambios no se observaron en el grupo C al final del estudio. Del mismo modo, el análisis entre grupos mostró una diferencia significativa para HG, FEMQ, STS10, 6MWT, BDI y EQ-5D. No observamos cambios relevantes en los datos bioquímicos ni antropométricos, en la medicación antidepresiva ni en los parámetros de adecuación dialítica a la finalización. Conclusiones: 1) El programa adaptado de ejercicio físico intradiálisis mejoró la fuerza muscular, la capacidad funcional y la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud de nuestros pacientes ancianos en HD. 2) Aun en población anciana, nuestros resultados realzan los beneficios del ejercicio físico en los pacientes en HD. 3) Ante un paciente anciano en HD, merece la pena considerar la realización de ejercicio físico adaptado intradiálisis como una parte más del cuidado integral en HD.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Background: Elderly patients on haemodialysis (HD) are a steadily increasing group. They show a high complexity, dependency and comorbidity. Multiple benefits from exercise in HD patients have been reported; however, they have not been specifically evaluated in an elderly population. Objective: To assess the effect of an adapted low intensity intradialytic exercise programme on muscle strength, functional capacity and health-related quality of life in our elderly patients (&gt; 80 years) on HD. Material and methods: HD patients were non-randomly assigned to an exercise training group (E) or a control group (C) in a 12-week single-centre prospective study. E included a combined exercise programme using balls, weights, elastic bands and cycle movements in the first 2 hours of HD sessions. C group patients received standard HD care. Endpoints were: 1) main biochemical data; 2) maximum quadriceps length strength (MQLS) and hand-grip (HG); 3) functional capacity tests: "Sit to stand to sit" (STS10) and "six-minutes walking test" (6MWT); 4) Beck Depressive Inventory (BDI); and 5) Health-related quality of life questionnaire: EuroQol-5D (EQ-5D). Results: A total of 22 patients were included (50% men). Mean age was 83.2 years; patients had received HD for 44.1 month. Charlson index was 9.5. Main aetiology was diabetes mellitus (36.4%). Eleven patients were assigned to E group and 11 to C group. No related adverse effects were observed. At the end of the study, E group showed an overall improvement in tests (*P<.05): MQLS 10.5 ± 7.6 vs. 12.9 ± 10.1 kg, HG* 16.6 ± 8.7 vs. 18.2 ± 8.9 kg, STS10* 29.9 ± 10.6 vs. 25 ± 7.87 sec, 6MWT* 14.6%, 234.4 vs. 274.7 m, BDI* 14.4 ± 11.5 vs. 11.7 ± 10.8 and EQ-5D 49 ± 19.1 vs. 59.5 ± 20.3. No similar changes were observed in C group. Significant differences between groups were also found for HG, MQLS, STS10, 6MWT, BDI and EQ-5D. No significant changes were found in biochemical and anthropometric data, antidepressant treatment or suitable dialysis parameters at the end of the study. Conclusions: 1) An adapted low intensity exercise programme improved muscle strength, functional capacity and health-related quality of life in our elderly patients on HD. 2) Our results highlight the benefits from exercise in HD patients even in this elderly population. 3) In elderly patients on HD, it is worth considering an adapted low intensity intradialytic exercise programme as a part of a comprehensive care.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
