<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952013000400010</identifier>
<datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Barril-Cuadrado,Guillermina]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Puchulu,M. Bernardita]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sánchez-Tomero,José A.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Enfermedad renal crónica]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Ratio fósforo/proteína]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Fósforo dietético]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.33 n.3 2013]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2013-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952013000400010</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Tablas de ratio fósforo/proteína de alimentos para población española. Utilidad en la enfermedad renal crónica]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Table showing dietary phosphorus/protein ratio for the Spanish population. Usefulness in chronic kidney disease]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Antecedentes: Las guías K/DOQI recomiendan el uso del ratio fósforo/proteína de los alimentos para un buen control del fósforo de la dieta. Existe evidencia de tablas con el ratio fósforo/proteína. No existe hasta el momento una tabla de alimentos habituales en la población española con la estimación del ratio. Objetivos: Estimar el ratio fósforo/proteína de alimentos de uso general en la población española y establecer su utilidad en la selección de alimentos para los pacientes con enfermedad renal crónica. Método: Las tablas con el ratio fósforo/proteína se han elaborado a partir de dos fuentes de datos de composición de alimentos españolas. Se ha considerado la composición química por cada 100 g de alimento crudo. Las tablas no incluyen el fósforo de los aditivos. No se eliminaron los alimentos con ratio fósforo/proteína elevado para poder establecer una comparación entre los distintos alimentos de cada grupo. Resultados: Se encuentran comprendidos en las tablas. Conclusiones: La prescripción dietética de los pacientes con enfermedad renal crónica debería tener en consideración no solo el valor absoluto de fósforo del alimento en cuestión, sino también el ratio fósforo/proteína de cada alimento y el total de la dieta. Cuanto más «natural» sea la dieta, más fácil será que alcance un ratio fósforo/proteína aceptable y mayor probabilidad de ser menor de 16 mg/g, no aumentando la morbimortalidad. Resulta evidente la necesidad de establecer un programa educativo sobre fuentes de fósforo y nutrición en el que la tabla pueda ser una herramienta útil para el equipo multidisciplinar que atiende al enfermo renal.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Background: The K/DOQI guidelines recommend the use of phosphorus/protein food ratios for proper control of dietary phosphorus. Evidence exists from tables with phosphorus to protein ratios for common foods. No such table exists for common foods consumed by the Spanish population with ratio estimations. Objectives: To estimate the phosphorus to protein ratio in foods commonly used by the Spanish population and to establish its usefulness in the selection of foods for patients with chronic kidney disease. Method: Tables with the phosphorus to protein ratio were prepared from two data sources concerning Spanish food composition. We evaluated chemical composition per 100g of raw food. The tables do not include phosphorus additives. No foods with high ratio of phosphorus to protein were eliminated in order to allow comparisons between different foods from each group. Results: Shown in the tables. Conclusions: The dietary prescription for patients with chronic kidney disease should take into consideration not only the absolute phosphorus value of food consumed, but also the phosphorus to protein ratio of each food and the total amount of phosphorus in the diet. The more "natural" a diet is, the more likely that the patient will reach an acceptable phosphorus to protein ratio of less than 16mg/g, which does not increase mortality. There is clearly a need for an educational program on nutrition and phosphorus sources in which food ratio tables could be a useful tool for the multidisciplinary teams caring for renal patients.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
