<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952011000600007</identifier>
<datestamp>2012-03-06</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Berdud,I.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arenas,M.D.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Bernat,A.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ramos,R.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Blanco,A.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hemodiálisis]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Centro de diálisis]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hospital]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Guías clínicas]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.31 n.6 2011]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2011-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952011000600007</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Anexo a la Guía de Centros de Diálisis: Recomendaciones sobre la relación entre los centros de hemodiálisis extrahospitalarios y sus hospitales de referencia: Opinión del Grupo de Diálisis Extrahospitalaria]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Appendix to Dialysis Centre Guidelines: recommendations for the relationship between outpatient haemodialysis centres and reference hospitals: Opinions from the Outpatient Dialysis Group]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Introducción: Las distintas guías de actuación clínica promovidas por la Sociedad Española de Nefrología (S.E.N.) pretenden homogeneizar el seguimiento del paciente renal. Sin embargo, esta labor de homogeneización, en el caso del paciente sometido a tratamiento sustitutivo con hemodiálisis, se ve dificultada, entre otras razones, por la existencia de distintas compañías de diálisis, con centros ubicados en distintas ciudades, con distintos hospitales de referencia y distintos criterios de actuación en función de los conciertos existentes con la sanidad pública que difieren también entre las distintas Comunidades Autónomas. Una buena relación del centro concertado con su hospital de referencia permitiría conseguir la igualdad en el tratamiento del paciente dializado, al menos en esa localidad. La S.E.N., a través del Grupo de Trabajo de Hemodiálisis Extrahospitalaria, considera deseable, para garantizar una adecuada continuidad asistencial de estos pacientes, que exista una estrecha relación y comunicación entre hospitales de referencia y sus centros de diálisis. Estrategias de mejora: Condiciones de envío de pacientes de unos centros a otros. El paciente que inicia programa de hemodiálisis debería ser remitido desde el hospital de referencia con un acceso vascular definitivo óptimo para el tratamiento, debería llevar un informe actualizado en las últimas 24-48 horas antes del traslado y este informe debería incluir la información esencial para una buena asistencia nefrológica: principales patologías, serología vírica reciente (incluyendo virus de las hepatitis B y C [VHB y VHC] y virus de la inmunodeficienia humana [VIH]), parámetros de anemia y de metabolismo calcio-fósforo e iones, fecha de la primera diálisis, y número y fecha de las transfusiones sanguíneas recibidas. De la misma forma, el paciente que es remitido desde el centro de diálisis al hospital, tanto para un ingreso programado como para urgencias, debería llevar un informe actualizado que incluyera los principales diagnósticos, las últimas incidencias, serología vírica y analítica, pauta de hemodiálisis y tratamiento actualizados y el motivo de remisión al hospital. La existencia de una historia clínica única, informatizada y al alcance de ambas instituciones facilitaría esta situación, si bien no está totalmente al alcance de todos los centros y los hospitales. Por otra parte, existen cuestiones legales que habría que resolver. Atención continuada del paciente en diálisis. Para una buena atención a estos pacientes resulta fundamental que exista una vía de comunicación fluida entre el centro y el hospital, y no sólo con el servicio de nefrología. Las interconsultas de los pacientes que son sometidos a diálisis en los centros concertados, así como la solicitud de determinadas pruebas diagnósticas, deberían poder ser solicitadas directamente por el propio centro. Los resultados e informes de esas interconsultas también deberían llegar al centro. Sería deseable compartir protocolos de actuación comunes entre el hospital de referencia y sus centros de diálisis concertados. Estos protocolos deben incluir aspectos básicos del tratamiento del paciente renal (anemia, metabolismo mineral, accesos vasculares incluyendo infecciones de catéteres, etc., o plan de analíticas) como protocolo de trasplante, pruebas complementarias y otros particulares de la localidad. Esto no sólo unifica el abordaje de los pacientes, independientemente de dónde se le esté dializando, sino que también facilita el acceso a los datos de todos los pacientes de cara a ensayos clínicos y a trabajos de investigación. Acceso a la medicación. Los pacientes en diálisis precisan medicación de dispensación sólo hospitalaria, que es habitualmente suministrada, de acuerdo con el concierto, por el hospital de referencia. Sería recomendable que otra medicación no incluida en el concierto (antibióticos, urokinasa, suplementos nutricionales, etc.) fuera dispensada de la misma manera. Acceso al trasplante renal. La gestión de la lista de espera de trasplante, una vez el paciente inicie el tratamiento sustitutivo, debería hacerse como cualquier otro procedimiento, desde el centro de diálisis. Los nefrólogos de los centros, por tanto, deben conocer los protocolos y las novedades existentes en este sentido y participar de las reuniones que se hagan en cada hospital entre nefrología y urología. El protocolo de trasplante de cada localidad o cada Comunidad Autónoma debe seguirse en todos los pacientes, se realícela diálisis en el hospital o en un centro concertado. Características del trabajo en el centro. El médico que atienda a los pacientes en los centros de diálisis debe ser especialista en nefrología. Este tema, complicado, debe ser exigible en los conciertos de las Consejerías de Salud para garantizar la asistencia adecuada y equitativa de los enfermos que son sometidos a diálisis en centros concertados. Sólo en el caso de ausencia de nefrólogo se podría recurrir a un médico generalista con la adecuada formación en hemodiálisis. Esta formación debería, asimismo, estandarizarse. Más del 75% de los nefrólogos que trabajan en los centros están solos durante la jornada laboral y un 40% no coincide con ningún compañero durante toda la jornada. Habría que buscar, por parte de las empresas, fórmulas que favorecieran el contacto entre profesionales, tanto con el hospital como con nefrólogos de otros centros, y que permitiera el intercambio de ideas entre ellos. Formación. Los nefrólogos de los centros concertados tienen el deber y el derecho de investigar y de ampliar su formación de manera continuada para poder desarrollar y mejorar su labor asistencial. Dado que la mayoría de los pacientes en programa de hemodiálisis se encuentran en centros periféricos dependientes de hospitales de referencia, podría sugerirse una mínima rotación de los residentes de nefrología por algunos centros de diálisis concertados extrahospitalarios, previa acreditación para poder dar formación.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Introduction: The different clinical guidelines backed by the Spanish Society of Nephrology (SEN) attempt to homogenise the monitoring of renal patients. However, this effort to homogenise treatment has been obstructed in the case of renal replacement therapy patients on haemodialysis due to, among other reasons, the existence of several different dialysis providers, with private centres located in many cities, each with their own reference hospitals and different criteria for treatment based on the existing outsourcing services agreements with the public health service, which also differ between regions. A good relationship between a private dialysis centre and its reference hospital would lead to equal treatment for all dialysis patients, at least at that particular town. The SEN, through the efforts of the Grupo de Trabajo de Hemodiálisis Extrahospitalaria (Outpatient Haemodialysis Group), has prioritised a close relationship and good communication between reference hospitals and dialysis centres in order to guarantee proper continuity of the health care given to these patients. Strategies for improvement. Conditions for referring patients from one centre to another. A patient that starts a haemodialysis programme should be referred from a reference hospital with a definitive vascular access for optimising treatment, with a full report updated within 24-48 hours before the transferral, including essential information for providing proper nephrological treatment: primary pathology, recent viral serology (including hepatitis B and C virus [HBV and HCV] and human immunodeficiency virus [HIV]), parameters for anaemia and calcium-phosphorus metabolism, and ions, date of the first session of dialysis, and the number and dates of blood transfusions received. Furthermore, patients referred from the dialysis centre to the hospital, whether for programmed visits or emergency hospitalisation, should be accompanied by an updated report indicating the primary diagnoses, recent events, viral serology and laboratory analyses, updated haemodialysis and treatment regimens used, and the reason for transferral to the hospital. A single, digital clinical history that is accessible by both institutions would facilitate this situation, although this option is not completely available to all centres and hospitals. There are also legal issues to resolve in this aspect. Continued care for dialysis patients. Good communication between dialysis centres and hospitals is fundamental for achieving a proper level of care for dialysis patients, and not only with the nephrology department. The interconsultations of dialysis patients at each private centre, as well as the requests for diagnostic tests, should be able to be requested by the centre directly. The results and reports from these interconsultations should also be sent to the centre. It would also be best if the reference hospitals and their private dialysis centres shared common treatment protocols. These protocols should include basic aspects of the treatment of renal patients (anaemia, mineral metabolism, vascular accesses including catheter infections, etc., and laboratory tests), transplant protocols, complementary tests, and other components specific to each area. Not only would this generalise and unify the approach taken with dialysis patients regardless of where they are treated, it would also facilitate access to data on all patients regarding clinical trials and research studies. Access to medication. Dialysis patients require medications that are only given in the hospital setting, which is normally provided by the reference hospital, as per the agreement between institutions. It would also be recommendable that any other medications not included in the agreement (antibiotics, urokinase, nutritional supplements, etc.) be dispensed in a similar manner. Access to kidney transplant. The management of the transplant waiting list, once a patient starts renal replacement therapy, should be controlled from the dialysis centre, as in any other procedure. As such, the nephrologists from each centre should be familiar with the existing protocols and new developments in this context, and should participate in meetings with nephrology and urology departments in each hospital. The transplant protocol at each town/region should be followed for all patients, whether dialysis is undergone in a hospital or private centre. Characteristics of the work at dialysis centres. The doctor attending patients at each dialysis centre must be a specialist in nephrology. This complicated issue must be a requirement for agreements within the regional health system in order to guarantee a proper and equitable treatment of patients that receive dialysis in private centres. Only in the case of an absence of a nephrologist should a general practitioner be used, and this doctor must have adequate training in haemodialysis. This training should also be standardised. Over 75% of nephrologists that work at these centres are alone during the workday, and 40% never see another colleague during the whole shift. The administrators of these centres should seek out protocols that provide professional contact, both with the hospital staff and nephrologists from other centres, which would facilitate an exchange of ideas. Training. The nephrologists at each centre have the right and the obligation to perform research and to continuously expand their training, so as to develop and improve health care provision. Since the majority of patients in haemodialysis programmes are treated in outpatient centres that depend on reference hospitals, we might suggest a minimal rotation of nephrology residents in private outpatient dialysis centres, once accreditation has been given for providing this training.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
