<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952010000500012</identifier>
<datestamp>2011-01-20</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Borrego Utiel,F.J.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Segura Torres,P.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pérez del Barrio,M.P.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Serrano Ángeles,P.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sánchez Perales,M.C.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Garía Cortés,M.J.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pérez Bañasco,V.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Admisión]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Albúmina]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Desnutrición]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hemodiálisis]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hospitalización]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Inflamación]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.30 n.5 2010]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2010-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952010000500012</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[La pérdida de peso en pacientes en hemodiálisis tras su hospitalización tiene relación con la duración de la estancia y con el grado de inflamación]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Loss of weight in hemodialysis patients after hospitalisation is related with length of stay and degree of inflamation]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Introducción: En pacientes en hemodiálisis es frecuente observar pérdida de peso relacionada con el ingreso hospitalario. Nuestro objetivo fue cuantificar esta pérdida de peso y analizar con qué factores se relaciona. Pacientes y métodos: Seleccionamos a pacientes en hemodiálisis crónica, con ingresos hospitalarios por cualquier etiología con duración mínima de 4 días, recogiendo pérdidas de peso al alta, a las 2 y 4 semanas del alta, así como evolución de variables con interés nutricional (creatinina, albúmina, transferrina, nPNA) tras su alta. Resultados: Incluimos a 77 pacientes, con 67 &plusmn; 12 años y 30 &plusmn; 34 meses en hemodiálisis, 40 mujeres (51,9%) y 22 diabéticos (28,6%). La estancia hospitalaria fue 17,8 &plusmn; 12,6 días (mediana 12 días). El 70,4% mostraron pérdida de peso al alta y un 81,3% a las 4 semanas del alta, sin influir sexo ni diabetes. El peso disminuyó al alta -1,09 kg (IC 95%, -0,73 a -1,44), -1,64 kg (IC 95%, -1,21 a -2,07 kg) a las 2 semanas y -1,94 kg (IC 95%, -1,47 a -2,42 kg) a las 4 semanas. Tras el alta observamos un descenso de urea (antes del alta 134 &plusmn; 40 frente a después del alta 119 &plusmn; 36 mg/dl; p = 0,001), creatinina (antes del alta 8,1 &plusmn; 2,6 frente a después del alta 7,5 &plusmn; 2,6 mg/dl; p <0,001), fósforo (antes del alta 5,2 &plusmn; 1,7 frente a después del alta 4,3 &plusmn; 1,5 mg/dl; p <0,001), albúmina (antes del alta 3,70 &plusmn; 0,48 frente a después del alta 3,56 &plusmn; 0,58 g/dl; p = 0,05). La pérdida de peso a las 4 semanas se correlacionó con una mayor estancia hospitalaria (r = 0,41; p <0,001), mayor índice de masa corporal en el momento del ingreso (r = -0,23; p = 0,05) y menor albúmina en el ingreso (r = 0,39; p = 0,012) y con albúmina (r = 0,27; p = 0,05), creatinina (r = 0,30; p = 0,02) y nPNA (r = 0,47; p = 0,002) más bajos después del ingreso. Albúminas más bajas en el momento del ingreso se correlacionaron con mayores descensos de la creatinina después del ingreso (r = 0,42; p = 0,009) y con una estancia más prolongada (r = -0,61; p <0,001). Con análisis multivariante, la pérdida de peso se asoció con mayor duración de estancia y con potasio sérico antes del ingreso. Conclusiones: La hospitalización de pacientes en hemodiálisis provoca una pérdida significativa del peso corporal debido a una probable pérdida de la masa muscular. La mayor estancia hospitalaria y el estado inflamatorio durante el ingreso son los factores que se relacionan con el deterioro nutricional que sufren los pacientes en hemodiálisis durante su hospitalización.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Background: It is frequent to observe that hemodialysis patients suffer important loss of weight during hospital stay. This issue has not been investigated previously. Our aim in this study was to analyze factors associated with this loss of weight and what changes occur after admission in biochemichal parameters with nutritional interest. Patients and methods: We retrospectively selected patients undergoing chronic hemodialysis who were admitted at hospital for acute or chronic pathologies, with a minimum length of stay of 4 days, taking only one episode of admission per patient. We chose loss of weight observed at hospital discharge, at 2 and 4 weeks later and we also collected routine laboratory data and adecuacy parameters before and after the hospital admission and basic biochemical parameters in the first week of hospital stay. Results: We included 77 patients, with 67&plusmn;12 years and 30&plusmn;34 months in dialysis. Forty (51,9%) were female (51,9%) and 22 diabetics (28,6%). Length of stay was 17,8&plusmn;12,6 days (median 12). There were 70,4% patients who suffered a loss of weight at discharge and 81,4% at 4 weeks, without differences in sex or diabetes. Weight decreased significantly with a mean of -1,09 kg (95%CI -0,73 to -1,44). After 2 weeks the loss of weight was -1,64 kg (95%CI -1,21 a -2,07 kg) and after 4 weeks was -1,94 kg (95%CI -1,47 a -2,42 kg). Comparing parameters before and after admission, we observed a significantly decrease in serum urea levels (before 134&plusmn;40 vs after 119&plusmn;36 mg/dl; p= 0,001), creatinine (before 8,1&plusmn;2,6 vs after 7,5&plusmn;2,6 mg/dl; p<0,001), phosphate (before 5,2&plusmn;1,7 vs after 4,3&plusmn;1,5 mg/dl; p< 0,001) and albumin (before 3,70&plusmn;0,48 vs after 3,56&plusmn;0,58 g/dl; p=0,05), without changes in adequacy parameters. Greater loss of weight at 4 weeks from discharge was correlated with larger length of stay (r= 0,41; p<0,001), greater body mass index at admission (r= -0,23; p=0,05) and lower serum albumin at admission (r= 0,39; p= 0,012). It was also correlated with a lower serum albumin (r= 0,27; p=0,05), lower creatinine (r= 0,30; p= 0,02) and lower protein intake (nPNA) (r= 0,47; p= 0,002) after discharge. Lower serum albumin levels at admission were correlated with greater decreases of creatinine after discharge (r= 0,42; p= 0,009) and larger length of stay (r= -0,61; p<0,001). Employing multivariate analysis we found that loss of weight was associated to length of stay and serum potasium levels before admission. Conclusions: Hospitalization of hemodialysis patients have a negative nutritional impact causing a significant loss of weight, probably reflecting a reduction of muscle mass. We found that length of stay in hospital is a basic factor associated with this nutritional impairment. The pathologies promoting hospitalization could influence this derangement through inflammation but this hypothesis should be investigated.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
