<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952012000800014</identifier>
<datestamp>2013-01-21</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Egocheaga,M. Isabel]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alcázar,Roberto]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lobos,José M.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Górriz,J. Luis]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Martínez-Castelao,Alberto]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pastor,Ana]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Martínez,Isabel]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caballero,Fernando]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sánchez-Celaya,Marta]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Atención Primaria]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Nefrología]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Guía de consenso S.E.N.-semFYC]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Enfermedad renal crónica]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Prevención]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Guías clínicas]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Detección precoz]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Seguimiento]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.32 n.6 2012]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2012-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952012000800014</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Conocimiento y aplicación en la práctica real del Documento de consenso S.E.N.-semFYC sobre la enfermedad renal crónica]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Awareness and implementation in daily practice of the S.E.N.-semFYC consensus document on chronic kidney disease]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Antecedentes: En el año 2007 la Sociedad Española de Medicina Familiar y Comunitaria (semFYC) y la Sociedad Española de Nefrología (S.E.N.) realizaron un documento de consenso para disminuir la variabilidad en la práctica clínica en la detección, tratamiento y derivación de la enfermedad renal crónica (ERC). Objetivos: Evaluar a los dos años de su publicación el conocimiento, difusión, grado de acuerdo y aplicación del Documento de consenso S.E.N.-semFYC sobre la enfermedad renal crónica. Métodos: Estudio transversal, descriptivo y observacional realizado en 476 médicos, incluyendo médicos de Atención Primaria (AP) y nefrólogos, mediante encuesta de opinión. Resultados: De los 326 médicos de AP y 150 nefrólogos encuestados, 51,1 % y 89,6 % respectivamente conocían el Documento de consenso. El 70,8 % de los nefrólogos lo considera muy necesario, con alto grado de acuerdo con sus contenidos. Los médicos de AP valoran más su utilidad práctica (63,2 % AP vs. 52,1 % nefrólogos). El mayor grado de desconocimiento en AP (> 20 % de los encuestados) incluye recomendaciones sobre la idoneidad del estudio ecográfico en varones con ERC mayores de 60 años y sobre los criterios de derivación a Nefrología. El grado de aplicación de las recomendaciones entre ambos especialistas resulta muy variable, siendo superior en nefrólogos. Edad, sexo, ámbito de trabajo, experiencia profesional, hábitat poblacional y presión asistencial no se asociaron con diferencias en el conocimiento, percepción de necesidad y aplicación del consenso. Conclusiones: Esta encuesta constata que el grado de difusión del documento S.E.N.-semFYC sobre ERC es mejorable, sobre todo en AP. Su aplicación puede modificar la práctica clínica. Se han identificado varios aspectos críticos en la evaluación y la derivación de los pacientes con ERC sobre los que deberían establecerse estrategias de difusión y formación continuada por las sociedades científicas implicadas.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Background: In 2007, the Spanish Society of Family and Community Medicine (semFYC) and the Spanish Society of Nephrology (S.E.N.) created a consensus document in order to reduce the variability in clinical practices for the detection, treatment, and referral of cases of chronic kidney disease (CKD). Objectives: To evaluate the level of awareness, dissemination, agreement, and application of the S.E.N.-semFYC consensus document on chronic kidney disease. Method: Ours was a cross-sectional, descriptive, and observational study carried out among 476 primary health care doctors and nephrologists using a survey. Results: Of the 326 primary care doctors and 150 nephrologists surveyed, 51.1% and 89.6% respectively knew of the consensus document. A total of 70.8% of nephrologists considered the document to be highly necessary, and were very much in agreement with the content. Primary care (PC) doctors placed more value on the practical usefulness of the document (63.2% PC vs. 52.1% nephrologists). The sections that reported the greatest level of unfamiliarity among primary care doctors (>20% of those surveyed) included recommendations regarding the suitability of ultrasound examinations in male patients with CKD older than 60 years of age and in regards to the criteria for patient referral to the nephrology department. The level of application of the recommendations set forth in the document varied widely between the two specialties, with greater compliance among nephrologists. Age, sex, field of medicine, professional experience, the population treated, and health care workload were not significantly associated with differences in awareness, perceived need, or application of the consensus document. Conclusions: This survey demonstrates that the level of implementation of the S.E.N.-semFYC consensus document for CKD has much room for improvement, above all among primary care physicians. The application of this consensus document can improve clinical practice. Several critical aspects have been identified in the evaluation and referral of patients with CKD that must be addressed through the establishment of strategies for disseminating information and continued training for the scientific societies involved in treating these patients.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
