<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952014000300012</identifier>
<datestamp>2014-07-31</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Torregrosa,José-Vicente]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[González-Parra,Emilio]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[González,M. Teresa]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cannata-Andía,Jorge]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Fósforo]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Carbonato de lantano]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Captores de fósforo]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Diálisis]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.34 n.3 2014]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2014-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952014000300012</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Estudio REFOS: eficacia y seguridad del carbonato de lantano en la práctica clínica en España]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[REFOS study: efficacy and safety of Lanthanum Carbonate in clinical practice in Spain]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[El carbonato de lantano es un potente captor de fósforo que en ensayos clínicos ha mostrado eficacia y seguridad para el manejo de la hiperfosforemia, aunque existen pocos datos en la práctica clínica habitual. El objetivo del estudio fue evaluar, en la práctica clínica habitual, su eficacia y seguridad en pacientes en diálisis. Se recogieron, retrospectivamente, datos de 15 meses de seguimiento, correspondientes a los 3 meses previos al inicio del tratamiento con carbonato de lantano y 12 meses después del inicio. Los datos incluían valores séricos de calcio, fósforo, fosfatasa alcalina, PTH, enzimas hepáticas y hemograma, así como la dosis diaria prescrita de carbonato de lantano, la medicación concomitante, el cumplimiento terapéutico y los eventos adversos. Se incluyeron 674 pacientes, de los cuales completaron el estudio 522. Los abandonos se debieron en mayor medida a trastornos gastrointestinales (26 %) e hipofosfatemia (19 %). El fósforo sérico disminuyó de 6,4 ± 1,7 mg/dl (inicio) a 4,9 ± 1,4 mg/dl (12 meses) (p < 0,001). Al final del seguimiento el 47 % se encontraba dentro del rango de fósforo deseado (3,5-5 mg/dl). No hubo variaciones significativas en el resto de los parámetros. Dosis inicial de carbonato de lantano: 1900 mg/día, y dosis final: 2300 mg/día. Las variables que se asociaron de forma independiente con la fosforemia final fueron el fósforo sérico basal y el cumplimiento terapéutico. Respecto a la seguridad, se observaron 238 efectos adversos leves o moderados que ocurrieron en 117 pacientes, estando el 88 % relacionado con alteraciones gastrointestinales. En conclusión, el carbonato de lantano reduce los valores séricos de fósforo en pacientes en diálisis con un buen perfil de seguridad y aceptable adherencia a este, siendo los trastornos gastrointestinales el efecto adverso más frecuente.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Lanthanum carbonate is a powerful phosphate binder that has shown efficacy and safety in clinical trials for hyperphosphataemia management, although there are few data in regular clinical practice. The study's objective was to evaluate, in regular clinical practice, its efficacy and safety in patients on dialysis. We retrospectively collected data from 15 months of monitoring, corresponding to 3 months prior to the start of treatment with lanthanum carbonate until 12 months after the start. Results included values of serum calcium, phosphorus, alkaline phosphatase, iPTH, hepatic enzymes and haemogram, as well as the daily-prescribed dose of lanthanum carbonate, the concomitant medication, treatment compliance and adverse events. 647 patients were included of which 522 completed the study. Abandonment, for the most part, was due to gastrointestinal disorders (26%) and hypophosphatemia (19%). Serum phosphorus decreased from 6.4 ± 1.7mg/dl (start) to 4.9 ± 1.4mg/dl (12 months) (P<.001). At the end of the monitoring period, 47% were within the desired phosphorus range (3.5-5mg/dl). There were no significant variations in the remaining parameters. Initial dose of lanthanum carbonate: 1900mg/day; and end dose: 2300mg/day. The variables independently associated with phosphataemia were baseline serum phosphorus and treatment compliance. In relation to safety, we observed 238 slight or moderate adverse effects in 117 patients, with 88% linked to gastrointestinal abnormalities. In conclusion, lanthanum carbonate reduces the serum phosphorus values in patients on dialysis with a good safety profile and acceptable adherence to that profile, with gastrointestinal disorders being the most frequent adverse effect.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
