<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952010000500014</identifier>
<datestamp>2011-01-20</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Albalate,M.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pérez García,R.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sequera,P. de]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alcázar,R.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Puerta,M.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ortega,M.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mossé,A.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Crespo,E.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hemodiálisis]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Catéter tunelizado]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Prevención]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Bacteriemia]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.30 n.5 2010]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2010-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952010000500014</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[¿Hemos olvidado lo más importante para prevenir las bacteriemias en pacientes portadores de catéteres para hemodiálisis?]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Have we forgotten the most important thing to prevent bacteremias associated with tunneled hemodialysis catheters?]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[La bacteriemia relacionada con el catéter (BRC) en pacientes en hemodiálisis (HD) es una complicación grave. Existen múltiples publicaciones que abogan por el uso de diferentes medidas farmacológicas para su prevención, pero muy pocas sobre la importancia de las medidas de precaución universal. El objetivo de este trabajo es mostrar la baja tasa de incidencia de BRC obtenida con la aplicación estricta de un protocolo de cuidados de catéter tunelizado (CT) por un personal bien entrenado en una nueva unidad de hemodiálisis. Durante 20 meses se aplicó un protocolo de manejo de CT por personal de enfermería cualificado. Se utilizaron un total de 42 CT en 32 pacientes. El tiempo total de seguimiento fue de 8.372 días en los que ocurrieron dos episodios de BRC: 0,24 eventos/1.000 días-catéter. El trabajo muestra cómo sólo con medidas de precaución universal pueden lograrse tasas de BRC dentro de la excelencia.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Bacteremia associated with tunneled central venous catheters (CVC) is a major complication in hemodialysis patients. Strategies that aim to prevent catheter-related bacteremia (CRB), ranging from the application of topical antibiotics to the use of different catheter-lock solutions, have been studied, but limited interest has been shown about following standardization of aseptic care and maintenance of CVC by experienced staff. This study reports CRB incidence obtained with a strict infection prophylaxis protocol based on universal precautions against infection adopted in our Unit by qualified nursing hemodialysis staff. During a period of 20 months, 32 patients received 42 CVC. There were 2 CRB, with an incidence of 0,24 CRB/1000 days-catheter. This study shows that an optimal catheter-use management reduces the incidence of CRB to excellent rates. The use of a protocol directed to vigorously protect the catheter at the time of usage by specialized teams is critically important and is highly recommended.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
