<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S0211-69952013000600003</identifier>
<datestamp>2013-11-07</datestamp>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Teruel-Briones,José L.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Fernández-Lucas,Milagros]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rivera-Gorrin,Maite]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ruiz-Roso,Gloria]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Díaz-Domínguez,Marta]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rodríguez-Mendiola,Nuria]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Quereda-Rodríguez-Navarro,Carlos]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hemodiálisis]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Diálisis peritoneal]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Función renal residual]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[&#946;2-microglobulina]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Anemia]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Española de Nefrología]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Nefrología (Madrid)  v.33 n.5 2013]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2013-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0211-69952013000600003</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Evolución de la función renal residual con una pauta incremental de diálisis: hemodiálisis frente a diálisis peritoneal]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Progression of residual renal function with an increase in dialysis: haemodialysis versus peritoneal dialysis]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Objetivo: El objetivo principal del estudio es el análisis de la evolución de la función renal residual según la técnica de diálisis (diálisis peritoneal o hemodiálisis) y la frecuencia del tratamiento (dos o tres sesiones de hemodiálisis a la semana). Como objetivos secundarios hemos estudiado la evolución de la concentración sérica de &#946;2-microglobulina y la respuesta de la anemia a los agentes eritropoyéticos. Material y métodos: Se incluyeron 193 enfermos no anúricos, que comenzaron tratamiento renal sustitutivo con diálisis en nuestro hospital entre el 1 de enero de 2006 y el 31 de diciembre de 2011, y tuvieron un seguimiento superior a tres meses. De ellos, 61 enfermos (32 %) iniciaron tratamiento con dos sesiones de hemodiálisis a la semana, 49 enfermos (25 %) con tres sesiones de hemodiálisis a la semana y 83 enfermos (43 %) con diálisis peritoneal. Se midió el filtrado glomerular como la media de los aclaramientos renales de urea y creatinina. Resultados: El ritmo de descenso del filtrado glomerular fue igual en los enfermos que comenzaron tratamiento con la pauta de dos sesiones de hemodiálisis a la semana y con diálisis peritoneal (mediana 0,18 ml/min/mes) y fue superior en los enfermos que iniciaron tratamiento con tres sesiones de hemodiálisis a la semana (mediana 0,33 ml/min/mes, p < 0,05). A lo largo de toda la evolución, la tasa de filtrado glomerular no mostró diferencias entre el grupo que comenzó con dos sesiones semanales de hemodiálisis y el grupo de diálisis peritoneal, y fue inferior en el grupo que comenzó tratamiento con tres sesiones de hemodiálisis a la semana con significación estadística durante los primeros 24 meses de seguimiento. En los tres grupos de enfermos la concentración de &#946;2-microglobulina fue aumentando conforme disminuía el filtrado glomerular y fue más elevada en el grupo de tres sesiones de hemodiálisis a la semana durante los primeros 12 meses de seguimiento. En todos los controles realizados hubo una correlación negativa entre la concentración de &#946;2-microglobulina y el filtrado glomerular (p < 0,001). La dosis de eritropoyetina se relacionó negativamente con el filtrado glomerular. Los enfermos que comenzaron con dos sesiones de hemodiálisis a la semana necesitaron una dosis menor de eritropoyetina que los enfermos que iniciaron tratamiento renal sustitutivo con tres sesiones a la semana. La dosis de eritropoyetina en el grupo de diálisis peritoneal fue inferior a la del grupo de dos hemodiálisis a la semana, a pesar de mantener un filtrado glomerular similar. Conclusiones: Los enfermos que comienzan tratamiento con dos sesiones de hemodiálisis a la semana experimentan el mismo ritmo de descenso de la función renal residual que los enfermos tratados con diálisis peritoneal. La evolución de la concentración de &#946;2-microglobulina es paralela a la del filtrado glomerular. Los enfermos tratados con dos sesiones de hemodiálisis necesitan una dosis de eritropoyetina menor que los que reciben tres sesiones a la semana, pero significativamente superior a la de los enfermos tratados con diálisis peritoneal, lo cual indica que la respuesta de la anemia a los agentes eritropoyéticos no solo está relacionada con la función renal residual, sino también con otros factores inherentes a la técnica de diálisis.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Objective: The main objective of the study was to analyse the progression of residual renal function according to the dialysis technique (peritoneal dialysis or haemodialysis) and the frequency of treatment (two or three sessions of haemodialysis per week). As secondary objectives, we studied the progression of the serum concentration levels of &#946;2 microglobulin and the response of anaemia to erythropoietic agents. Material and method: 193 non-anuric patients were included and began renal replacement therapy with dialysis in our hospital between 1 January 2006 and 31 December 2011, with a follow-up period of over three months. 61 patients (32%) began treatment with two haemodialysis sessions per week, 49 patients (25%) with three haemodialysis sessions per week and 83 patients (43%) with peritoneal dialysis. The glomerular filtration rate was measured as the mean of the renal clearances of urea and creatinine. Results: The rate of decrease in glomerular filtration was the same in patients who began treatment with two haemodialysis sessions per week and with peritoneal dialysis (median 0.18ml/min/month) and it was higher in patients who began treatment with three sessions of haemodialysis per week (median 0.33 ml/min/month, P<.05). Throughout progression, the glomerular filtration rate did not display differences between the group that began with two weekly sessions of haemodialysis and the group on peritoneal dialysis, and it was lower in the group that began treatment with three sessions of haemodialysis per week with statistical significance during the first 24 months of follow up. In the three patient groups, &#946;2- microglobulin concentration increased as the glomerular filtration rate decreased and it was higher in the group on three weekly haemodialysis sessions for the first 12 months of follow up. In all the controls carried out, there was a negative correlation between the &#946;-2 microglobulin concentration and the glomerular filtration rate (P<.001). The erythropoietin dose was negatively related to glomerular filtration. Patients who began with two sessions of haemodialysis per week required a lower dose of erythropoietin than patients that began renal replacement therapy with three weekly sessions. The erythropoietin dose in the peritoneal dialysis group was below that of the group of two weekly haemodialysis sessions despite maintaining a similar glomerular filtration rate. Conclusions: Patients who begin treatment with two sessions of haemodialysis per week experience the same rate of decrease in residual renal function as patients treated with peritoneal dialysis. The progression of the concentration of &#946;2-microglobulin is parallel to that of the glomerular filtration rate. Patients treated with two haemodialysis sessions require a lower dose of erythropoietin than those who receive three sessions per week, but a significantly higher dose than those treated with peritoneal dialysis, which suggests that the response of anaemia to erythropoietic agents is not only related to residual renal function, but also to other factors that are inherent to the dialysis technique.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
