<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S1135-76062005000100003</identifier>
<datestamp>2008-12-02</datestamp>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mavárez-Cardozo,MG.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Espina de Fereira,AI.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Barrios-Ferrer,FA.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Fereira-Paz,JL.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[dípteros y coleópteros necrófagos]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Entomología Forense]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[etapas de descomposición]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Intervalo Post-Mortem]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[neotrópico]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Asociación de Médicos Forenses de Andalucía]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Cuadernos de Medicina Forense  n.39 2005]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2005-01-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1135-76062005000100003</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[La Entomología Forense y el Neotrópico]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The Forensic Entomology and the Neotropic]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[La Entomología Forense ha alcanzado un estatus importante dentro de las ciencias forenses. Los países del Neotrópico tienen una composición faunística y ambiental, diversa y extensa. Sin embargo, son escasos los trabajos referentes a la sucesión de insectos en cadáveres en esta región. Los objetivos de este trabajo fueron recopilar información bibliográfica acerca de las investigaciones realizadas en el Neotrópico y en otras latitudes, y compararlos con los obtenidos en observaciones realizadas en pequeños cadáveres de mamíferos en la Parroquia Juana de Ávila, Municipio Maracaibo, Estado Zulia, Venezuela. Hay autores que han reportado que la estacionalidad es un factor decisivo en países como Canadá, Estados Unidos y España en contraste con países del Neotrópico, como Perú y Colombia. Esto determinó una variabilidad importante tanto en las oleadas de artrópodos, como en la duración de cada una de las etapas de descomposición de los restos. En nuestras observaciones de campo, Chrysomya sp. apareció desde el primer día y sus larvas se mantuvieron en ese estado hasta el séptimo y octavo día donde empezaron a formar pupas, las cuales emergieron entre el noveno y décimo día. Se observó la presencia muy dispersa y pobre del adulto, después del décimo día. Se concluyó que Chrysomya sp. fue la especie dominante sobre los otros dípteros carroñeros y el indicador principal del intervalo postmortem (I.P.M.), durante los primeros diez días en los cadáveres estudiados.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Forensic Entomology has reached an important status within the forensic sciences. The Neo-tropical countries have a vast and diverse environmental and faunal composition. Nevertheless, the studies regarding the insect succession in cadavers in this region, are scarce. The objective of this paper is to gather information regarding the research performed in the Neo-tropics and in other latitudes, and to carry out observations in the cadavers of small mammals in the Parish of Juana de Avila, Municipality Maracaibo, State Zulia, Venezuela. A bibliographic revision was made as well as the daily captures and observations of insects in the carcasses of three domestic cats and four laboratory rats during a period of ten days. Other authors have reported that the seasonal variations is a decisive factor in countries such as Canada, the United States and Spain, in contrast to what happens in Neo-tropical countries such as Peru and Colombia. This has determined an important variability in the arthropod waves, as well as in the duration of each of the decomposition stages of the remains. According to our field observations, Chrysomya sp, appeared on the first day and a larva stage was maintained until the seventh and eighth day when they started to create pupas, which emerged between the ninth and tenth day. After the tenth day, a poor and disperse presence of the adult could be observed. The conclusion was that Chrysomya sp was the dominant specie among the other carrions dipterous and the principal indicator of post-mortem interval (P.M.I.) during the first ten days in the cadavers under study.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
