<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S1139-76322010000400002</identifier>
<datestamp>2010-12-27</datestamp>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alberola López,S.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pérez García,I.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Casares Alonso,I.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cano Garcinuño,A.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Andrés de Llano,J.M.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Mochila escolar]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Dolor de espalda]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Infancia]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Asociación Española de Pediatría de Atención Primaria]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Pediatría Atención Primaria  v.12 n.47 2010]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2010-09-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1139-76322010000400002</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Mochilas escolares y dolor de espalda en la población infantil]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[School backpacks and back pain in child population]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Introducción: el peso de las mochilas preocupa por el esfuerzo físico que realizan los niños y su relación con problemas de espalda. El objetivo es conocer los hábitos del uso de mochilas y su relación con el dolor de espalda en población escolar. Material y métodos: estudio observacional en 4 consultas pediátricas. Se analizan variables demográficas, antropométricas y se administra un cuestionario. Resultados: son 159 niños, 80 varones y 79 mujeres, de 11 y 14 años, que cursan 5º de Educación Primaria (EP) y 2º de Educación Secundaria (ESO). El 69% acude al colegio andando, el 80% lleva la mochila en ambos hombros, el 59% se cansa y el 62,3% refiere dolor de espalda. La puntuación del dolor es 5 (escala 0-10). La mochila pesa 6,3 ± 2 kg. El peso relativo (porcentaje de peso en relación al peso del niño) es 13,4% ± 5,5 y no difiere entre sexos, medio urbano o rural, pero sí- entre grupos de edad (15,5% en EP, 11,6% en ESO, p < 0,001) y centro (público: 14,3%; concertado: 12,3%; p = 0,02). No encontramos diferencias en el peso con o sin dolor (13,8% versus 12,7%; p = 0,19) ni en la presencia de dolor por sexo o edad. No se encuentra asociación entre dolor y horas de tele/ videojuegos pero sí entre dolor y horas de deporte extraescolar (más horas, menos dolor: OR [odds ratio]: 0,23; IC [intervalo de confianza] 95%: 0,08-0,7). Existe diferencia en la puntuación de síntomas psicosomáticos, mayor en los que sufren dolor (OR 1,37; IC 95%: 1,2-1,6). Conclusiones: el peso de las mochilas es el 13,4% ± 5,5 del peso del niño. Aunque no encontramos asociación entre dolor y peso, este influye en la sensación de malestar en la infancia y debe considerarse un problema de salud.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Introduction: backpacks' load is worrisome because of the physical effort made by children and its potential relationship with back problems. Objectives: to know the habits of school bags' use and its relationship with back pain in the paediatric school population. Material and methods: cross-sectional observational study in three primary care centres. We analyze anthropometric and demographic variables and we fill in a questionnaire based on previous studies. Results: one hundred and fifty-nine children were included. They were 80 males y 79 females, aged 11 and 14 years, studying 5º year in primary level (EPO) and 2º year in secondary level (ESO). Sixty-nine percent of them walk to school, 80% carry the backpack in both shoulders, 59% feel tired with it, and 62.3% refer back pain. The mean score of pain is 5 (scale: 0-10). Schoolbag weight is 6.3 kg ± 2. Relative weight is 13.4% ± 5.5 of the children's body weight and it is not different neither between genders, nor in urban-rural site, but differs between ages (15.5% in 5º EPO, 11.6% in 2º ESO; p < 0.001) and type of school (public: 14.3%; concerted: 12.3%; p = 0.02). The relative weight is higher in those students who feel that the backpack is too heavy (14.2% versus 12.2%; p = 0.02), but it is not in those who refer back pain (13.8% versus 12.7%; p = 0.19). We have not found neither differences in back pain with gender and age, nor association between pain and number of TV/videogames watching hours. There is association between pain and number of extra-school sports hours (the more hours, the less pain: OR [odds ratio]: 0.23; CI [confidence interval] 95%: 0.08-0.7). There is a difference in the psychosomatic symptoms score (scale: 0-18), being higher in those who have back pain (OR 1.37; CI 95%: 1.2-1.6). Conclusions: the schoolbags' relative weight is 13.4% ± 5.5. Although we have not found association between back pain and backpack weight, it affects the feeling of discomfort in childhood and it must be considered a health problem.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
