<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S1139-76322012000300005</identifier>
<datestamp>2012-10-10</datestamp>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eddy Ives,L. S.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Moral Peláez,I.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Brotons Cuixart,C.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[de Frutos Gallego,E.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Calvo Terrades,M.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Curell Aguilà,N.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Obesidad]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Índice de masa corporal]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Adolescencia]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Hábitos alimentarios]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Ejercicio físico]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Estudios de seguimiento]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Asociación Española de Pediatría de Atención Primaria]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Pediatría Atención Primaria  v.14 n.54 2012]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2012-06-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1139-76322012000300005</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Hábitos de estilo de vida en adolescentes con sobrepeso y obesidad: Estudio Obescat]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Life style habits of overweight and obese adolescents: Obescat study]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Objetivo: evaluar la eficacia de una intervención educativa sobre hábitos de estilo de vida para reducir el índice de masa corporal en adolescentes. Pacientes y métodos: ensayo clínico de un año de seguimiento realizado en 48 centros de Atención Primaria de Cataluña. Participaron 174 adolescentes entre 10 y 14 años con sobrepeso u obesidad; 87 aleatorizados al grupo intervención y 87 al grupo control. La intervención fue de carácter educativo (hábitos alimentarios y de ejercicio físico) y se realizó en la visita inicial, y a los 1, 3, 6, 9 y 12 meses de seguimiento. Variables de resultados: cambios en hábitos alimentarios y ejercicio físico, cambios en el índice de masa corporal (IMC) y en el perímetro abdominal. Resultados: edad media 11,81 años (desviación estándar [DE]: 1,21) y 50% mujeres. Completaron el seguimiento 125 participantes (71,8%). Los Z-scores de IMC disminuyeron en ambos grupos (p < 0,001), de un valor medio inicial de 2,35 (DE: 0,46) a 2,06 (DE: 0,60). Los Z-scores de perímetro abdominal se redujeron en ambos grupos: en el grupo intervención de una media de 2,06 a 1,77, y en el grupo control de 2,06 a 1,82 (p < 0,001). La intervención educativa mejoró los hábitos alimentarios (aumento ingesta de fruta, disminución de dulces y de la ingesta de alimentos cuando se está aburrido). La actividad física disminuyó (p = 0,002). Conclusiones: la intervención educativa fue efectiva para reducir el IMC y el perímetro abdominal en ambos grupos. Hubo mejoría en los hábitos alimentarios, pero no en la práctica de ejercicio.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Objective: to assess lifestyle habits and efficacy of a lifestyle intervention to reduce body mass index (BMI) in adolescents. Methods: one-year randomized control trial, carried out in 48 pediatric primary care units of Catalonia. A random sample of 174 overweight and obese adolescents 10-14 years old was taken, 87 allocated to intervention group (IG) and 87 to control (CG). IG received baseline lifestyle counseling (food and exercise habits) plus 5 interventions at months 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12. CG received baseline intervention plus final control. Main outcome measures were: change in lifestyle habits, and of BMI and waist circumference (WC). Results: mean (SD) age was 11.81 (1.21) and 50% were female. A total of 125 participants (71.8%) completed follow-up at 12 months. Body mass index Z-scores showed a significant reduction in both study groups (p < 0.001), reducing from a mean (SD) initial value of 2.35 (0.46) to final value of 2.06 (0.60), which represents approximately 12% reduction of baseline Z-score, without showing differences between study groups. The waist circumference Z-score also was statistically reduced in both study groups: IG from mean 2.06 to 1.77; and CG from mean 2.06 to 1.82 (p < 0.001). Counseling improved many food habits (highlighting increase of fruit, decrease of candy and habit to pick-on food when bored) but physical activities decreased instead of increasing (p = 0.002). Conclusions: lifestyle counseling was effective to reduce body mass index and waist circumference in adolescents, regardless of intensity. Counseling improved food habits, but not exercise.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
