<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S1139-76322016000100005</identifier>
<datestamp>2016-06-07</datestamp>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Carpio Gesta,M.ª Luisa]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Redondo Gallego,M.ª Jesús]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ballester i Diez,Ferrán]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Maltrato infantil]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Violencia doméstica]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Mortalidad infantil]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Niños hospitalizados]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Asociación Española de Pediatría de Atención Primaria]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Pediatría Atención Primaria  v.18 n.69 2016]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2016-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1139-76322016000100005</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Mortalidad e ingresos hospitalarios por violencia de los menores de 15 años en la Comunidad Valenciana (2007-2011)]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Mortality and hospital admissions by violence among children under 15 years in the Valencian Autonomous Community (2007-2011)]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Introducción: la violencia contra la infancia jamás es justificable y puede prevenirse actuando sobre los desencadenantes de comportamientos violentos. Conocer su magnitud y características posibilita emprender cambios que contribuyan a reducir su frecuencia y gravedad. Métodos: se analiza la mortalidad y los ingresos hospitalarios por violencia en menores de 15 años en el periodo 2007-2011 en la Comunitat Valenciana. Resultados: se contabilizaron 12 defunciones y 156 ingresos. Murieron tres veces más niños que niñas. Los fallecimientos fueron más frecuentes en los menores de un año, seguido del grupo de 10-14 años. Los seis casos de suicidio ocurrieron en el grupo de 10-14 años y los métodos utilizados fueron: ahorcamiento, estrangulamiento o sofocación y saltar desde lugar elevado. Los homicidios fueron el doble en niños y niñas de 0-9 años. Ingresaron por violencia dos veces más las niñas, siete veces más en el grupo de 10-14 años, tres veces más los extranjeros, dos veces más los residentes en medio rural y dos veces más si tenían riesgo de exclusión social, siendo estas diferencias estadísticamente significativas. Los ingresos por violencia autoinfligida fueron el doble (intento de suicidio) que por agresiones. Conclusiones: el número de casos es de gran importancia epidemiológica y de salud pública. En la violencia contra la infancia se manifiestan los ejes de desigualdad en salud y la necesidad de mejorar la declaración y la coordinación de todos los ámbitos de la atención a los menores. Es relevante relacionar las distintas fuentes de información, devolverla a los profesionales y formarlos.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Introduction: violence against children is never justifiable and can be prevented by acting on the factors that trigger violent behaviors. Knowing the magnitude and nature of violence against children allows us to undertake the changes that will contribute to reduce their frequency and severity. Methods: in this paper, mortality and hospital admissions due to violence among children under 15 years from 2007 to 2011 in the Valencian Autonomous Community is analysed. Results: 12 deaths and 156 hospital admissions were registered. Boys' deaths were three times as frequent as those of girls. The deaths were more frequent in children under one year, followed by 10-14 years. The six cases of suicide occurred in the group of 10-14 years and the methods used were: hanging, strangulation or suffocation; and jumping from a high place. There were twice as many killings in children of 0-9 years. Girls were hospitalized due to violence twice as often as boys. Hospital admissions were 7 times as high in the group of 10-14 years, 3 times as high in foreigners, twice as high in residents in rural areas and twice as high if there was a risk of social exclusion, with these differences being statistically significant. Hospital admissions from self-inflicted violence were twice as high (attempted suicide with drugs) as those caused by assault (beating, stabbing and rape). Conclusions: the number of cases found is numerically small but of great epidemiological and public health significance. Axes of inequality in health due to violence in childhood are highlighted as well as the need of improving the notification of cases and the coordination in all areas related to childcare. Linking information sources and returning the information to professionals is relevant as well as training them.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
