<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S1139-76322011000100006</identifier>
<datestamp>2011-05-04</datestamp>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[González de Dios,J.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[González Alcaide,G.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Valderrama-Zurián,J.C.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Aleixandre-Benavent,R.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Bibliometría]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Factor de impacto]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Pediatría]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Revistas biomédicas]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Asociación Española de Pediatría de Atención Primaria]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Pediatría Atención Primaria  v.13 n.49 2011]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2011-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1139-76322011000100006</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Aproximación al "impacto" de las revistas biomédicas en Pediatría: estudio de los indicadores bibliométricos en Journal Citation Reports-Science Citation Index 2009]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[An approach to the impact of biomedical journals in Pediatrics: study of bibliometric indicators in the Journal Citation Reports-Science Citation Index 2009]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Introducción: el factor de impacto (FI) es el indicador bibliométrico más conocido. El objetivo de nuestro estudio es realizar un análisis cienciométrico de las revistas pediátricas en Journal Citation Reports-Science Citation Index (JCR-SCI) del año 2009. Material y métodos: estudio de las 63 categorías de Biomedicina y Ciencias de la Salud en JCR-SCI del año 2009, por medio de la Web of Knowledge. Indicadores bibliométricos: revistas, artículos, citas, FI, índice de inmediatez, vida media y revistas con mayor FI en cada categoría. Análisis pormenorizado de las revistas pediátricas en la categoría Pediatrics y situación de las revistas pediátricas en español en JCR-SCI 2009. Resultados: se constatan 94 revistas en la categoría Pediatrics en el año 2009, con 12 648 artículos, 297 188 citas, FI medio de 1,406, índice de inmediatez de 0,344 y vida media de 7,2. Clasificación por FI: 29 revistas con FI entre 0 y 0,999; 37 con FI entre 1 y 1,999; 24 con FI entre 2 y 3,999; y 4 con FI > 4. Los mayores FI corresponde a Journal of American Academy of Child & Adolescent Psychiatry (J Am Acad Child Psy), con 4,983; Archives of Pediatrics & Adolescent Medicine (Arch Pediatr Adol Med), con 4,726; y Pediatrics, con 4,687. El mayor número de artículos publicados en 2009 corresponde a Pediatrics, con 752; Journal of Pediatric Surgery (J Pediatr Surg), con 512; y Pediatric Blood & Cancer, con 398. El 56% de las revistas pediátricas procede de Estados Unidos y hasta el 95% está publicado en inglés. La única revista pediátrica en español es Anales de Pediatría, que presenta por primer año un FI oficial de 0,363, y ocupa el puesto 89 en la categoría Pediatrics y, respecto a las 59 revistas españolas en JCR-SCI, el puesto 43. Conclusiones: encontramos una aceptable representación de revistas pediátricas (310) sobre las 7347 volcadas en JCR-SCI 2009. La categoría Pediatrics presenta unos indicadores cienciométricos discretos en el conjunto de las categorías de Biomedicina y Ciencias de la Salud. El primer paso de una revista pediátrica española (la inclusión de Anales de Pediatría en JCR-SCI 2009) ya se ha dado; se analizan estrategias editoriales para mejorar su calidad, importancia e impacto. Debido a las importantes limitaciones del FI, conviene analizarlo desde una perspectiva bibliométrica multidimensional y en la perspectiva de su área de investigación.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Introduction: the Impact Factor (IF) is the most commonly used bibliometric index. The objective of this paper is to carry out a scientometric analysis of Paediatric journals included in 2009 Journal Citation Reports (JCR) Science Edition. Material and methods: 63 Biomedical and Health Science categories of 2009 JCR Science Edition have been analysed by means of Web of Knowledge platform. Bibliometric indexes: number of journals, number of articles, total cites, IF, Immediacy Index, Cited Half-Life and the most IF journals of each category have been identified. Paediatric category journals and Anales de Pediatria, the only Paediatric Spanish journal in JCR 2009 Science Edition, have been accurately analysed. Results: 94 journals covered in 2009 JCR Paediatrics category were analysed, which have published 12,648 articles and have been cited 297,188 times. The mean IF was 1.406, Immediacy Index was 0.344 and Cited Half-Life was 7.2. Twenty-nine journals had an IF between 0 and 0.999, 37 journals an IF between 1 and 1.999, 24 journals an IF between 2 and 3.999, and finally, 4 journal had an IF > 4. J Am Acad Child Psy (4.983) presented the highest IF, followed by Arch Pediatr Adol Med (4.726) and Pediatrics (4.687). Pediatrics was the most productive journal (752 articles), followed by J Pediatr Surg (512) and Pediatric Blood & Cancer (398). 56 percent of journals were from the USA and English was the main language for 95 percent of surveyed journals. Anales de Pediatría was the only Spanish journal, indexed since 2009 which an IF of 0.363, ranked 89th of 94 in Paediatric category and 43th of 59 among Spanish journals indexed in 2009 JCR Science Edition. Conclusions: paediatric journals have an acceptable representation in 2009 JCR Science Edition database (310 of 7,347 journals). Paediatric category scientometric indicators were rather moderate compared to biomedical and Health Science categories. Anales de Pediatria has been included in JCR since 2009, so the first step is done. Editorial strategies for improvement of quality, importance and journal impact are discussed. Numerous criticisms have been made of the use of an impact factor due to its limitations. IF must be carefully analysed, from a multidimensional perspective considering IF is highly discipline dependent.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
