<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S1699-695X2010000100003</identifier>
<datestamp>2010-05-24</datestamp>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Garcés Redondo,Guillermo]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colán Colán,César]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sánchez Oropesa,Arancha]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Gómez Suanes,Gabriela]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Canchig Pilicita,Freddy E.]]></dc:creator>
<dc:creator><![CDATA[López de Castro,Francisco]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Industria Farmacéutica]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Marketing]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Visitador Médico]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Atención Primaria de Salud]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Castellano-Manchega de Medicina de Familia y Comunitaria]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Revista Clínica de Medicina de Familia  v.3 n.1 2010]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2010-02-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1699-695X2010000100003</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Opinión sobre la Visita Médica de los Médicos de Atención Primaria de Toledo]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Toledo Primary Care Doctors' Opinion on visits from Pharmaceutical Representatives]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Objetivo: Conocer la actitud y el comportamiento de los médicos de atención primaria frente a la Industria Farmacéutica (IF), especialmente frente a los visitadores médicos. Diseño: Descriptivo transversal, basado en entrevistas telefónicas. Emplazamiento: Atención Primaria. Área de Salud de Toledo. Mediciones principales: El cuestionario contenía ítems sociodemográficos y laborales, frecuencia de recepción de visitadores, actitud frente a la información facilitada, opinión sobre la utilidad e influencia en la prescripción de la visita médica, comportamiento ante estrategias de marketing y percepción de problemas éticos en la relación médico-IF. Resultados: Sólo se pudo entrevistar a 63 médicos (25,9%). La edad media fue de 50,7 años (65,1% varones). Eran tutores el 30,2%, trabajaba en el medio rural el 57,1% y tenía especialidad vía MIR el 31,6%. El 98,4% recibía a los visitadores, a diario el 77,8% a diario. El promedio semanal de visitas era de 10,2. Sólo el 16,1% afirmó revisar la información facilitada por los visitadores. Un 45,2% refirió contrastarla posteriormente. Los visitadores aparecen como segunda fuente de información sobre medicamentos. La opinión sobre la utilidad de la visita es mayoritariamente favorable. El 59,7% no suele asistir a cursos organizados por la Industria. Cuando asisten a un Congreso, el 60,3% reconoce hacerlo invitado por la IF. Suelen asistir a comidas/cenas de los visitadores el 61,9%. El 55,6% ha recibido alguna vez un regalo de los laboratorios. La mayoría reconoce la influencia del marketing farmacéutico en la prescripción ajena. El 50,8% considera que no existen problemas éticos en la relación médico-IF. Conclusiones: La visita está prácticamente generalizada y es considerada útil por muchos. Se subestima su influencia en la prescripción propia. Las prácticas de marketing están ampliamente extendidas y aceptadas. La mitad no reconoce problemas éticos en la relación con la IF.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Objective: To determine primary care doctors' attitude and behaviour towards the Pharmaceutical Industry (PI), especially pharmaceutical sales representatives. Design: Cross-sectional descriptive study, based on telephone interviews. Setting: Primary care, Toledo Health Area. Main measurements: The questionnaire included items on socio-demographics, work, frequency of visits, attitude toward the information provided, opinion on the usefulness of the visit and influence on prescribing habits, attitude towards marketing strategies and opinion on the ethical issues concerning the doctor-PI relationship. Results: Only 63 (25.9%) doctors were interviewed. The mean age was 50.7 years (65.1% male). Thirty two point two per cent were tutors, 57.1% worked in rural areas and 31.6% were specialised through the Spanish medical residency training (MIR) system. Ninety eight point four percent received visits from pharmaceutical representatives, 77.8% every day. The average number visits per week was 10.2. Only 16.1% of doctors said they reviewed the information provided by the representatives and 45.2% said they checked it at a later time. The representatives are the second source of information on medicinal products. Most doctors had a favourable opinion on the usefulness of the visit. Fifty nine point seven percent of doctors did not usually attend courses organised by the PI. Sixty point three percent said they attended a Congress when invited by the PI. They usually go to lunches/dinners when invited by the representatives. Fifty five point six percent have received a gift from pharmaceutical companies at some time. Most doctors recognised the influence of pharmaceutical marketing on other doctors' prescribing habits. Fifty point eight percent consider that there are no ethical issues concerning the doctor-PI relationship. Conclusions: Visits from pharmaceutical representatives is widespread and many doctors consider them to be useful. The doctors thought the visits had little influence on their own prescribing habits. Half of the doctors considered there were no ethical issues concerning the doctor-PI relationship.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
