<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<scielo-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>oai:scielo:S1699-695X2008000300004</identifier>
<datestamp>2009-04-20</datestamp>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata>
<oai-dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai-dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:creator><![CDATA[Angora Mazuecos,Francisco]]></dc:creator>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Directivas Anticipadas]]></dc:subject>
<dc:subject><![CDATA[Atención Primaria de Salud]]></dc:subject>
<dc:publisher><![CDATA[Sociedad Castellano-Manchega de Medicina de Familia y Comunitaria]]></dc:publisher>
<dc:source><![CDATA[Revista Clínica de Medicina de Familia  v.2 n.5 2008]]></dc:source>
<dc:date>2008-10-01</dc:date>
<dc:type>journal article</dc:type>
<dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1699-695X2008000300004</dc:identifier>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Voluntades Anticipadas vs. Instrucciones Previas o Testamento Vital en Atención Primaria de Salud]]></dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Early Wills vs. Previous Instructions or Living Wills in Primary Care]]></dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Hipótesis y Objetivo. La Ley reconoce los derechos fundamentales de los pacientes terminales, que pueden ejercer Declaración de Voluntades Anticipadas (DVA) como autentica planificación que respeta el sistema de valores personales del paciente al poder decidir morir dignamente, pero escoger en libertad requiere información clínica sobre las opciones posibles. Si actualmente pocas personas ejercen DVA, es debido a que aún no se dan las condiciones optimas que demanda la legislación sobre voluntades anticipadas (VA). El objetivo principal del estudio ha sido descubrir conocimientos sobre: prolongación de la vida, derecho legal y moral a elegir una muerte digna, limitación del esfuerzo terapéutico (LET) y existencia en Castilla La Mancha de la posibilidad de ejercer DVA. Diseño. Estudio de intervención primaria, por muestreo consecutivo sobre pacientes de 65 y más años, emplazado en APS; mediante un "curso de introducción informativa sobre VA" y "encuesta sobre conocimientos e impresiones de VA", previos y posteriores al curso. Emplazamiento. Centro de Salud urbano de Ciudad Real capital. Mediciones principales. Variables sociodemográficas (edad, sexo, vivienda, convivencia, trabajo principal antes de jubilarse). Conocimientos e impresiones sobre VA y DVA, antes y después del curso. Resultados. Mayoritariamente viven en domicilio propio, tienen estudios elementales, y dedicación previa de amas de casa, funcionarios, técnicos y peones. Previo a la sesión el 60% desconocía las VA y su posibilidad de ejercer declaración. Encuestados y familiares vivirían más tranquilos declarando VA. Quieren registrar sus preferencias en la historia de APS. Tras el curso, la mayoría tiene claras las limitaciones legales, profesionales y morales de las VA. El 70% optaría por ejercer DVA ante funcionarios del registro de VA (Delegación de Sanidad). Conclusiones. Los mayores saben poco de VA (situación expectante). El personal y el ámbito de la APS resultan idóneos para informar-asesorar sobre VA y DVA. Procedería ampliar el estudio a otras franjas etarias.]]></dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Hypothesis and objective. The legal system recognizes the fundamental rights of terminal patients or dying ones who can use a Declaration of Early Wills (DEW), that corresponds to a certified planning of treatments which respects the system of personal values of the patient, who can decide to die with dignity. However, a free choice requires clinical information about the possible options available. Nowadays, the reason why few people use DEW is that most of the legally required conditions are not fulfilled. The main objective here is to find information about the prolongation of life, legal and moral right to die with dignity, limitation of therapeutic effort (LTE) and the possibility of using DEW in Castilla-La Mancha. Design. Study of primary intervention using a consecutive sample of patients over 65, from a PC setting, using "an informative course that gives an introduction to the EW" and "a survey of knowledge and opinions about EW", before and after the course. Setting. Urban Health Centre of Ciudad Real. Main Variables. Socio-demographic variables (age, gender, house, cohabitation, main job before retirement). Knowledge about and impressions of EW and DEW, before and after the course. Main findings. The vast majority live in their own houses, have elementary studies and worked as housewives, civil servants, technicians or unskilled labourers. Before the session, 60% did not know anything about EW and the possibility of declaring them. People participating in the survey, and relatives, would feel more reassured if they could declare EW. They would like to register their preferences in their PC records. After the course, the vast majority have a better understanding of the legal, professional and moral limitations of the EW. A total of 70% would sign DEW before civil servants of the EW registry (Health office). Conclusion. Individuals have little information about EW at present. Staff from PC are the most suitable people to inform patients about them and should give the patients a real freedom of choice. This study should be broadened to include people of different ages.]]></dc:description>
<dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/</dc:rights>
</oai-dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</scielo-document>
